I designed this to be literally the best
resolve video on the internet at the end
of this video you'll be able to create
your own projects and D Vinci resolve
and you're going to know the basics of
every step in the process from importing
media to making a rough cut to polishing
your story to adding visual effects and
Graphics color grading audio mixing and
all the way into final render I'm going
to move really slow and show you every
step and you can even download Media and
follow along with me just click the
download Media Link Down Below in the
description there are two versions of
resolve there's the paid version which
is $300 and the free version which is
free and you should be able to use the
free version of resolve to do pretty
much everything in this video this is
essentially a course that we've offered
on ground control for the last couple
years called introduction to D Vinci
resolve but we've decided to update the
course and put it here on YouTube
absolutely free why is that well my
specialty and what we do at Ground
Control is we teach Fusion we teach the
fusion page of resolve that's making
effects and graphics and fancy stuff for
your videos and it's an amazing part of
the app but there's kind of a decent
learning curve that's why we have an
in-depth beginner Fusion course called
Fusion Zero to Hero we've brought
hundreds of students through that course
and we're convinced it's the very best
way to learn Fusion when you're ready
but if you don't know resolve you're not
really ready to learn Fusion yet so my
hope is that you'll pick up resolve and
you'll start to love it and use it to
make videos every day and pretty soon
you're going to want to learn Fusion
that's where we can really help you out
for now if you're just getting started
with resolve my name is Casey and I've
helped people over the last 10 years
like millions of people learn how to use
resolve and I'm really excited to dig in
and have some fun so let's go so before
we dive in here's what you need first of
all to use resolve you need a pretty
darn good system and I know pretty darn
good is subjective but we're talking
about like a mid-range gaming PC
something with a good graphics card one
of the later Macs like a M1 or M2 Mac
something that's pretty beefy you don't
want try to use resolve on an
underpowered computer you're just going
to have a bad time and resolve likes
resources that's really the only bad
side about resolve is you have to have a
really good system so that's a
prerequisite next thing is you got to
download resolve you can go to
Blackmagic design.com ssupport and
scroll down here under latest downloads
and somewhere around here you should
find the latest version of Da Vinci
resolve in this course I'm going to be
using resolve
18.64 and you can get the free version
and follow along or you can get the
studio version I'm going to be using the
studio version but most of what I'm
doing is exactly the same in the free
version and if it's not I'll tell you
the other thing that's going to be
helpful is a little bit of knowledge of
editing and how video production works
and media and that kind of thing that's
going to do nothing but help you on your
resolve Journey here if you've used
other video editing apps or even if
you've done something like edit audio or
you've made music anything with tracks
and a timeline that's going to really
help however we are going to go really
slow and I'm going to try and explain
everything the best I can even for
beginners but just saying the the other
thing is time this is going to be a
decent chunk of time a lot longer than
this video is going to take because you
will need to put in some time to
practice to actually get these Concepts
so if you have these first two That's
essential if you have a little bit of
knowledge of how some Media stuff works
and the time to put in you are going to
do great now if you want to follow along
with me you can click the link down in
the description it's going to be one of
the first links and it's going to say
download project and media files here
and that'll take you to a page where you
can sign up to download a zip file that
includes a Dr now this Dr file is a d
Vinci resolve archive and it's basically
just a folder that contains the project
file as well as the media files now the
project file in resolve is just the
project itself with the timelines bins
edits compositions color grades all of
the kind of data on the things that
you've changed the things that you're
actually working on and the project file
is really really small the media files
are the things that are really big so
things like video clips audio clips
photos sound effects that kind of thing
and that stuff is separate from the
project file but in this case for our
download here it's all put in one folder
that's renamed a drra file you can
double click on this Dr file and it'll
open up in resolve and it should look
something like this once it does you can
double click it to open it and you
should have a project that looks
something like this and you'll be able
to follow along with me again this file
is going to be in a zip file and so
you'll need to unzip the file then
double click on this or on this screen
screen and resolve you can rightclick
and go to restore project archive then
you can find thisd folder and hit open
and that'll open it just like that so
with all of that you should be set to
follow along now if you're looking at
this and you're like gosh there's just a
lot here and I don't even know where to
start before we even dive into the
interface let's just take a step back
here and take a look at what the heck
we're even trying to do in this whole
learning resolve thing first of all what
is resolve well resolve is an endtoend
post-production program and it lets you
do I mean all of this stuff that you see
here all of these Hollywood movies have
been edited or at least color graded
inside of Da Vinci resolve and I mean
obviously it's a very professional very
awesome tool to use to create any kind
of video or film or TV show or whatever
you want to make as far as media and the
big idea here is that all of these post-
production things that you would have to
do to make a movie you can do all inside
of one app from your basic edits to
color grading to to audio mixing and
fair light to compositing infusion all
of that stuff lives inside of resolve so
you don't have to go to separate apps
you don't have to round trip into you
know a different Suite of software I you
know some kind of Suite that lets you be
creative I you know if there were such a
thing uh might do it differently but I
think this is the real advantage to
resolve is it's everything you need all
in one place what's also really cool is
that you can collaborate with people
that you're working with over the
Internet or through your network and you
can all share a project file and you can
all work on it at the same time so in
this little example this guy is working
on Fusion stuff while this person's
doing color and another person can be
editing or working with media and this
can all happen on the same project at
the same time and so it really
simplifies a lot of the headaches that
you would have to go through to work on
a big project with a team but resolve is
also awesome if you're just working by
yourself the interface is broken up into
different pages and each page has a
different job for post-production so the
cut and the edit Pages have to do with
actually putting your story together the
color page is for color correction the
fusion page is for doing compositing and
effects and explosions and all of those
fancy things and fair light is for
getting really detailed with your audio
mix and so these different tasks are
laid out from left to right in the app
in sort of the order that you would take
when you're actually creating something
starts with media and you would import
your media your your video and your
audio and put it in your project and
then you would edit it and put your
story together then you do the effects
then you do the color correction then
you do the audio mix and then finally
you would deliver it you would render it
out for other people to see and so I
love resolve I use it for my everyday
work been using it for years and it's a
really wonderfully design tool to create
YouTube videos television shows music
videos I mean even Hollywood movies it
just has all the tools you need all in
one place and almost everything is
available in the free version which is
just nuts pretty much all of the
Advanced color correction tools and all
the awesome stuff you can do in Fusion
all the super powerful audio mixing and
fair light as well as The Rock Solid
editing and resolve are available in the
free version without any watermarks or
trial periods or anything like that it's
just free it's just awesome there's all
kinds of cool hardware and stuff that
works with the resolve software there's
hardware for editing and for color and
even some super crazy stuff for audio
mixing comes in two versions the free
version and the paid version the paid
version is 295 the free version is free
and you may be wondering okay the free
version what's the catch there isn't
really a lot of catch honestly it can do
so much you can render up to Ultra HD
has all the color and it has so much in
it oh my gosh you can use it for
commercial work it's amazing but with
the studio you buy it one time it's $295
and it just gives you a little more of
the fanciness it has some more effects
it has some film grain it supports 10bit
video it has resolutions Beyond 4K and
it has some really cool different AI
driven effects and things like that it's
definitely worth it to pay the onetime
fee of $2.95 and you get free updates
too which is just crazy like I bought my
studio version back in I think resolve 9
and I've been using the same license and
now we're on resolve 18.6 crazy so yeah
if you don't know if you should get the
studio or not just get the free version
and play around with it and if you run
across a feature that is only in the
paid version it'll tell you and if you
just keep running into those features
then consider getting the paid version
but until then just use the free version
you're going to love it so with all that
out of the way let's dive into results
the first thing that you'll see when you
open resolve is something like this this
window here is called your project
manager this is where you can open
projects you can make new projects a lot
of stuff can happen if you rightclick on
the empty space here there's new project
new folder import project restore
project archive which we already talked
about and so this is where you'll you
know open a new project and save things
and that kind of thing now all of these
projects they live on a database or as
they call it a library nowadays you can
go over here on the left and click add
project library and you can tell it
where to put the project library and
it's just a folder that lives on your
hard drive where it puts all of your
project files all the project files and
everything are really small so you can
kind of put it wherever is good for you
but all of your projects are going to
live in that folder now this is kind of
weird for some people who might be used
to keeping their project on a certain
folder along with their media files and
doing their own project management but
it's really not that big of a deal you
can organize your projects here and it
keeps them all on the same folder and
then you have your media files wherever
you want on your system you can keep
those on a separate hard drive and that
kind of thing so if you have a big
external hard drive or a Nas or
something like that all your media files
stay on that part of the hard drive and
your projects all live in the library
for resolve if you do want to save out a
project and put it somewhere specific
you can right click on a project and go
to export project and that'll save a DRP
file which is a d Vinci resolve project
and then you can save that wherever you
want and then that's the way that you
could give a project to somebody else or
you know you can back it up and that
kind of thing so it's easy to do that
it's just you're kind of making a copy
of that project rather than actually
keeping the project itself on a separate
drive if you have any questions about
that leave them in the comments below
because I know that part can be kind of
tricky for some people one other thing
to notice about this project manager is
up here on the left it says local now
that means that this is on the project
Library that's on your system but if you
go over to these other tabs there's
Network and cloud and we'll skip Network
for this video but if you click on cloud
this will actually open up libraries
that you have shared on the Blackmagic
Cloud so in order to share a library you
have to make a library with your
Blackmagic account it's five bucks a
month but you can share this with as
many people as you want and they can all
work on the same project with you from
across the hallway or across the world
pretty crazy and it works exactly the
same as what we're going to be doing
just on the local but it's on the cloud
and there are some collaboration
features and that kind of thing that we
can get into later but it's actually
really nice really wellth thought out
system for sharing projects but I'm just
going to switch back to local and double
click on our project to open it up and
when you open your project it should
open up in the edit page or possibly
sometimes the cut page I think a new
project by default opens in the cut page
but this project that you download might
open up in the edit page kind of depends
on like what page you had open when you
saved this out or when you closed it but
let's take a look at the layout of
resolve biggest thing to notice right
now is this lower bar down here we have
the page buttons and when you click on
any of these buttons it will switch out
the entire interface for or a different
page so right now I'm in the edit page
but if I switch over to the media page
that switches to Media mode if I switch
to Fusion that switches over to fusion
color Fair light that kind of thing and
each of these pages is sort of like
opening up a completely different app so
they're specialized for a certain post-
production task just like you might open
up a dedicated audio program to work on
your audio you go to Fair light to work
on your audio for your project but the
big Advantage here is that all of these
Pages share the same timeline and so
here we can see we have our edit with
the kids looking at the little alien
puppet guy and if I switch over to color
this is the exact same timeline but in
the color page and so I don't have to
export anything I don't have to convert
anything if I want to do the audio for
this one I can just switch over to Fair
light and I can zoom this in and really
start working with the audio and so
that's a really important concept for
resolve is that all of these Pages they
share the same timeline and by default
it's whatever timeline you have open in
this page if you switch to a different
page that's going to open the same
timeline in the next page so I have
color page start here but if I switch to
edit page start that's going to be a
different timeline which actually
doesn't have anything and I switch over
to color there's nothing there Fair
light there's nothing there I can switch
timelines by going up here to the upper
right above our viewer and I can pick
which timeline I want that's going to
show me the most recent timelines that
I've opened and this project only has a
few timelines so we can see all of them
but I can also go over here to my media
pool on the left in my edit page and I
can find my different timelines and
double click on them from the media pool
to open those up I want to point out one
really important thing before we just
dive in here in the lower right there's
this settings Cog this is the project
settings this is very important if you
click on Project settings that brings up
all the settings that you want to make
sure you get right kind of before you
get started that's the best way to do it
there's ways to kind of mess with this
if you've already done some editing and
everything but for the most part you
want to make sure that your timeline
resolution is what you want mine is set
at 1920 by 800 because we have this
widescreen footage timeline frame rate
is 23976 which is what we shot at and I
definitely recommend opening this up and
playing it around and just looking at
all of the stuff you don't have to
understand all of it but go through here
and look at some of these things because
that will just help you get familiar
with where some of these little annoying
things that you might need to you know
switch a tick box or something this is
where a lot of those things are now
these settings have to do with just your
project that's why it's called the
project settings so this is stuff like
you know how big is the resolution of
the timeline and what's the frame rate
and if I put a smaller piece of footage
into this timeline what does it do does
it stretch up to fill the frame or does
it just leave it alone all of that kind
of stuff is controlled here in the
project settings and we'll be coming
back to this a couple times I'm sure if
this seems overwhelming for now don't
worry about it too much but one thing to
mention is if I click on this house I
can open up the project manager I'm
going to right click and say new project
I'll just say Untitled project when
you're looking at a blank project like
this it's a good idea just to go into
the project settings and set your
resolution if you want to work at you
know UHD switch it to UHD if you want to
do 24 for your frame rate kind of get
that all set up if you're going to work
with color management like we'll talk
about later now is a good time to set
that up really before you do anything
else and I'd say probably the most
important thing is the timeline frame
rate make sure that you set your frame
rate right because it's annoying to
change this later the resolution is not
that big of a deal a lot of the other
things aren't that big of a deal but the
timeline frame rate kind of a big deal
make sure to get that right and if you
don't know what get it right means it's
probably the same frame rate as you shot
at and if you don't know what frame rate
you shot at well you should probably pay
attention to that because different
frame rates give you different looks
we'll take a look at how to find a piece
of media's frame rate here later but for
now I'm going to switch back over to our
other project here our downloaded
project and let's just work through
these pages so we're going to start at
the very left with the media page just
click on that that'll open that up and
here's kind of the big concept here the
media page AG is designed to be a
workspace where you import media and you
manage it and you rename things and
organize things and kind of get your
Affairs in order before you start
editing you don't really have to use the
media page you could just stay in the
edit page and drag your media right into
the timeline and kind of start working
here but it is a nice way to be able to
just preview media that's on your hard
drive before you even have it imported
into your project and it gives you a
nice big interface to be able to go
through your folders and look at all
your footage organize things and look at
all of the data and the properties of
every clip and if you're into getting
organized you're going to be good
friends with the media page so let's
kind of break this down in the upper
lefthand corner we have our media
storage panel that's this part right
here and in this little list here you
can look at all of the hard drives on
your system and you can twirl down the
folder structures and you can preview
any of the media that's on your computer
if you double click on a piece of media
that's going to open it up here in this
viewer and you can scrub this and play
it back you can turn on the sound if it
has sound play that back and so this is
actually a really nice way to go through
and just see what footage you have
available if you Mouse over any of these
thumbnails you can kind of scrub through
the footage really easily you can just
kind of quickly look through what you
have you can grab this little slider up
here and make these previews a little
bigger or you can make them smaller
depending on what you want to do and
this works for video as well as audio
you can scrub through your audio like
this double click it to bring it up here
in the
viewer and yeah just a nice way to
preview things but so far none of this
media is actually in our project we
haven't imported it at all it's just on
our system now the media always stays on
our system we don't make copies of the
media or anything we haven't really
added it to our project like we haven't
told the project that we want to use it
if we do want to add something to our
project we can just grab it and drag it
down here to this lower part which is
our media pool now the media pool looks
a lot like this media storage right here
the difference is that this media pool
is a list of organized media that's
added to our project so this is the
media that we actually are going to use
we've told resolve that we don't want to
just look at this media on our hard
drive we're going to take this and we're
going to put it in a timeline we're
going to work with it and actually edit
it you can't work with something in
resolve until you've imported it into
resolve and anything that you have
imported goes into the media pool okay
so this is all of the footage and media
and everything that we have in our
sample project here and the media Pool
Works very similar to the media storage
you can Mouse over things and it gives
you a little preview you can double
click on them to open it up in the
viewer and you can scrub through you can
make these thumbnails bigger or smaller
you can switch it to list view or metad
dat View and you can look at all the you
know time code information and all of
that stuff for all of this footage and
so yeah you can get really detailed with
this stuff in list view I like that you
can look at all of these different
properties sort of in a spreadsheet here
you can right click on the top part and
change the different columns that you
want to show and man you can just get
really deep we could make this whole
course just on the media pool but again
all of this footage is actually imported
into the project now that means we can
work with it so we've learned about
three panels so far the media storage
which is just the media that's on your
system that you can preview here the
viewer where you can preview things and
the media pool which has all of the
media that you've put into the project
not copied out of the folders on your
system but you're just telling resolve
that you want to use it kind of adding
it to a to-do list almost in the upper
right we'll see we have these little
buttons up here and some of them are
white and some of them are gray if one
of these little headings is white it
means that its panel is showing right
now so audio when it's white it has the
meters and the waveform available and
when I click it it turns gray and it
closes that panel same thing with
metadata I have metadata open right now
and if I click that it closes it and
just makes room for the other panels and
that's how a lot of stuff in resolve
works is there's these buttons up here
and it opens and closes the different
panels now you can't grab the panels and
rearrange them like you can in other
software and I actually really like that
because that means that I can't ever
lose a panel it's always in the same
place so in the media page the metadata
panel is always here on the right now
metadata panel is if you double click on
a piece of footage that'll open that up
here in the metadata panel and it will
tell you all kinds of fancy information
about it bit depth and field dominance
and all these really really nerdy things
and you can even look for more nerdy
things if you click on this little list
arrow button there's all these different
categories of information here and I
like to switch it to shot and scene
because this is where you can kind of
write notes and categorize things and so
I can write a description of whatever
this is so it's you know roasting
marshmallows on the fire and I can put
in comments and keywords all kinds of
things I can color code this clip and I
can even put in data about what shot
this was what scene what take and angle
whether it's day or night and I can
really just kind of log my footage here
which for some projects might be to
totally Overkill and some projects might
be really good but you have the ability
to get organized based on each piece of
media right here in the metadata panel
so depending on how much information we
have and how much information we really
want to log and get organized we can
fill all this stuff in another panel is
the inspector panel the inspector this
is a really important panel this
controls the properties of whatever we
have selected there is a version of the
inspector in just about every page of
resolve so anything that you have
selected you adjust the properties of in
the inspector and we're going to be
dealing with this a lot but just as a
little intro you can select a piece of
media here in the media pool and zoom it
in and kind of change its zoom and its
position and everything here in the
media pool even before you add this to a
timeline and so you know that if you
really want this zoomed in like this and
you're never going to use the wider shot
you can just do this while you're kind
of organizing your media and that might
be helpful of course you can always
reset things by clicking this little
circle Arrow either the individual
property here next to these properties
or the circle Arrow Plus in the upper
right hand corner to reset everything
and with any of these controls I can
just grab this little text box and drag
left and right to change that value I
can hold alt to move a little bit slower
have a little bit finer control I can
also just double click on this and then
type it you know 05 like that and that
works with pretty much every kind of
control in resolve we also have a
capture panel which has to do with
actually capturing things from a film
scanner or a tape deck and we're not
going to get into that today mostly what
you need is the the inspector the
metadata panel and the media pool so
yeah to import things into resolve you
can go to the media storage and drag it
in from the media storage like that into
the media pool you can also take footage
just from your Explorer or finder window
and just drag this right into the media
pool like this and it does pretty much
the same thing now one thing you might
want to do in the media page is get
organized so you see how everything is
kind of put in these folders here these
are called bins and so if you right
click in the empty space in this context
menu you could say new in and that'll
just make a blank folder here and we'll
call this a camping footage just a
reminder you guys aren't going to have
this footage right here this is just
sort of a little demonstration here you
can select any footage you want to put
in the folder and just drag it in like
that double click on the folder to open
that up and then it adds it to this list
here this is the bin list and you can
quickly jump to any bin just by
selecting the bin like that now you can
make your own bins like this but there's
also something called smart bins now
smart bins are really cool by default
there's a couple of smart bins happening
if I twirl down collect here it'll
automatically kind of smart sort some of
my media so here's video clips here's
things with just audio and if you have
the studio version of resolve you can
right click on any piece of media and go
to audio classification analyze and that
will think about what kind of audio this
is and it will put it into the correct
category so this toilet flush would be
an effect right if I go to this upset
mom. wve go to audio classification
Analyze This is mostly dialogue if I
switch over here it's put this in the
dialogue folder because it's mostly
dialogue and so that can be really
helpful to kind of get yourself
organized just with those automatic kind
of things so I can just shift select all
of this right click say audio
classification analyze again this is
only in the paid version of resolve it
does this it's not essential but it is
kind of cool and if I go down here to
subcategories there's all these
subcategories that it makes and it's
pretty fun so like here's ones with a
lot of breathing here's ones with bodily
functions here's one from a boat
apparently it thinks that there's boat
sounds or cattle sounds and so it's not
perfect but it's kind of fun to see what
it thinks your audio contains right so
it thinks there's pigs and livestock and
sheep and everything so I don't know if
it's look there's toilet flushing though
we got toilet flushing rocked that was
amazing at toilet flushing so am
I and so that's kind of a cool thing you
could also I'll just twirl up this
collections here if you right click
under smart bins you can say add smart
bin you can make a smart bin based on
properties that you want to sort by it
doesn't really add these to a bin just
like you would normally add it to a
folder where it just kind of moves this
piece of media into the folder in the
media pool it actually is more like a
filter just kind of like these
collections are it's sort of like a
search filter so all of this audio isn't
really in the dialogue bin it's just
sorted by dialogue you can make a smart
bin if I say add smart bin and I could
do something like media pool properties
file name contains let's just say GC for
a ground control and that's going to
search for anything with GC in the name
and it's going to put those all together
right and you can even drill this down
more so anything that has GC in the name
and you know with shot and scene let's
say the scene is scene one so none of
that actually is tagged as scene one but
if I create this and then I go to my
media let's just grab something that
says GC GC house door open we can go to
scene and say scene one like this and
then now in our smart bin we have GC
with scene one and so we can get really
crazy and it's super organized and if
you're an OCD person oh baby you can
just go nuts so much fun another cool
thing that's sort of related to this is
you can do keywords so if we were to go
through here if I hold control select
all of these and say check and say drop
like this and hit save you should all
have the drop keyword on them yep under
our smart bins if I click on keywords
and then twirl this down we're going to
have keywords for various different
things so anything that has the keyword
drop will be in those smart bins we have
some keywords added for Clips with our
actress Gwen we have things tagged as
wide angle and so definitely play around
with this way of making smart bins
because especially if you have a bigger
project than this it's really helpful to
be able to organize things like this so
you can find stuff quickly organize
stuff by scene that kind of thing I'll
show you one other cool thing in the
media page before we get into the other
stuff this has already been done for you
but if you double click on a piece of
media you can open it up and if you
happen to be using a slate you can look
at the Slate numbers and so we have
scene 4 shot 8 take one and you can go
through and listen to your audio and
find scene 4 shot 8 take one which is
right here here and if you have separate
audio like this you can control select
both the audio that you want to sync and
the video that goes along with it and
then you can right click and go up to
Autos sync audio and then go down to
base on waveform and what that will do
you just barely even see it is it will
figure out where this audio syncs up
with the video and then it will link it
to it and it will just stick the audio
in place of the on camera audio so if I
double click on this and play this back
go check it
out um no you go check it out and so now
we have this nice secondary audio synced
with the lips and you can rightclick on
any of these clips go up to clip
attributes to change a bunch of stuff
but there's these tabs up top and if I
click on this second tab this audio tab
after you have it synced it's going to
say linked channel one can switch this
back to embedded Channel this is just
the on camera audio how it was recorded
just so we can hear the difference here
hit okay bring this up you go check it
out fine and so now we have the on
camera audio which is way worse and
again you can right click go up to clip
attributes and change this back to link
Channel anytime you want and what I like
to do is go through the audio in the
media page and figure out the scene and
shot and type this in for all of my
Clips as I import them into the project
and so if you have a project with
secondary audio like this it can really
really save you a lot of headaches later
if you just go through and organize them
like that and the media page is a great
way to do that and then you just match
them up right we can switch this to our
list View and I can right click on this
top part here and we'll just uncheck
most of these let's just uncheck almost
all of these cuz we don't care about
most of this we do care about scene shot
and take anything else we'll just we'll
keep on synced audio too like this and
now we have the shot and the scene and
the take and we can organize them by
shot and this way if we have everything
tagged the two clips that should sync up
are going to be right next to each other
the audio and the video you can see
scene and take are the same thing right
click say autosync audio based on
waveform boom sync that up kind of go
through here shift select both of these
Autos sync audio based on waveform Boom
like that and you can go through and
sync up everything before you even get
to editing and if you have a project
like this that has the secondary audio
especially something that's like a short
film like this this is a really great
way to do it no problem but you can go
through here and kind of get organized
and that's really what the media page is
for depending on what you're doing this
might be super useful or it might be way
Overkill again it's totally okay to skip
the media page and just go over to the
edit page and that's what we're going to
talk about next now let's talk about the
edit page of resolve now the edit page
is where we put together our story
editing is all about telling stories and
so when we make our movie we actually
put together the series of shots here in
the timeline this is sort of like the
Hub of all of the things that are going
to go into our project everything that
the person that is going to watch our
movie is going to see has to be here in
the timeline so if you're new to editing
I think it's really important to kind of
understand this concept I think this is
really helpful there is a difference
between what really happened in real
life or even what was shot if you know
you're shooting a narrative or something
like that and then the story is we tell
it events might have happened in a
certain order in real life but then we
can change the order as we put them in
the timeline and change How The Story
Goes so in real life maybe bill is
walking to his car right he opens his
front door then he waves to his neighbor
then he gets a phone call and then maybe
in real life he walks to his car and
then gets in the car we can choose to
tell our story exactly that way Bill
opens the door waves to the neighbor
gets a phone call walks to his car gets
in the car but we also have the freedom
to change things around so for instance
we could cut out the whole phone call
and then the story is Bill opens his
door waves to the neighbor walks to the
car gets in the car we could cut out the
neighbor part Bill opens the door walks
out to his car gets in the car we don't
even have to show him walking to the car
we could show that he opened the door
and then we can assume that he walked
the car and so we have all this Freedom
with how we tell our Story in real life
maybe we shot Bill getting in the car
and walking to his car on day one we
shot Bill getting a phone call on day
two and we shot him coming out of the
door and waving to his neighbor on day
three we you can put these in a
different order and because of the
context it changes the story and in
resolve here in the timeline that's
where we do this so let's take a look at
our
story w
w go check check it
out um no you go check it
out
fine
okay check it
out what was
that and so we have our story here the
two kids arrive on their bikes drop the
bikes and they see
something what do they see they see a
crashed
spaceship then they
react and they talk to each
other they decide to go check it out so
he starts walking toward the spaceship
we see his reaction and her
reaction and then as they get closer the
little door on the spaceship moves and
he jumps back and we have the reactions
again and that's how the story goes all
of this is pieced together from moments
that we shot all separately all in
different orders and we put these things
together to make a story most of these
were shot on the same night but for
instance this shot was shot a totally
different night but it all looks like it
works together so I'm harping on this a
lot because this is really the main
thing that happens in the edit page this
is where we put our story together we
take all of our unedited media and we
put it together together to make any
sense at all and this is where you'll
probably spend most of your time in
resolve so let's have a look at the
interface here I'm just going to go up
to workspace
and reset our UI
layout so that yours should look a lot
like mine and we're going to start with
what we already know here on the left
side of the screen we have our media
pool now this is exactly like the media
pool in the media page just instead of
down here like this it's over here on
the left
and we can do a lot of the media
management tasks and everything that we
would do in the media page right here in
the media pool I could right click on
the blank space and I have a lot of
different options here I can make new
timelines I can make new Fusion
composition I can make bins I can import
media I can do all kinds of stuff but
you can think about this as just like
your toolbox all the little pieces that
you can assemble live here on the left
under the media pool then of course
across the bottom we have our timeline
and this is where we actually put the
clips
the video clips and the audio clips
that's where we lay out our story in
time above that we have our toolbar and
this is how you switch out various modes
and options ways to interact with Clips
little preferences that kind of thing
we'll get into that in a little bit and
above that we have two viewers the
leftand viewer is our source viewer so
if we go over here to the media pool
double click on a piece of media we can
open that up here in our source viewer
and we can look at it from beginning to
end so this is a great way to to go
through a piece of media and decide
which parts you like which parts you
don't kind of scrub through it see if
this is going to work for your movie or
not this viewer on the right is our
timeline viewer and this is a preview of
what you'll actually see when you render
your project so as I play this playhead
we see it playing right here on the
right so this is like what your movie
looks like and this one over here is a
way to preview the little pieces of
media in your media pool up along the
top we have several different buttons
which open and close panels a couple to
note are the effects panel which kind of
comes in below the media pool and you
can actually just close the media pool
to have a bigger effects
panel and this is where you can do
things like grab titles so I can just
select titles and grab some text and
drag that
in and have some text over your movie
there's also different things like
different
transitions which will go in between
Clips here on your timeline as you play
it back it will give different
Transitions and of course there's
effects and so you can take an effect
and drop it on any clip in the timeline
like
this and that will apply that effect so
here we have this kind of camcorder
effect so if you want something to look
like it was shot on a camcord or
something like that that's a great way
to do that I'll just undo that for now
you can undo anything in resolve just by
hitting contrl Z at any point that's
where the effects live more on that in a
little bit over here on the right one
panel to note is the inspector now the
inspector is a very important panel
inside of resolve this is where you'll
find all of the properties for whatever
you have selected in the timeline so if
I select this clip right here that I'm
over right now and I push up this Zoom
that's going to zoom up our clip same
thing for rotation that kind of thing so
we have a bunch of different controls we
have transform controls which is just
kind of movement and rotation
we have cropping controls so I can crop
off a side of a shot if we want to do
like a split screen or something like
that and there are a few other different
options here which you can play with
yourself and we'll get into kind of
throughout this course but the things to
remember are when you have the inspector
open you're adjusting the properties of
whatever you have selected now that
might not be what you're looking at cuz
notice I have this clip selected in the
timeline but I have my playhead right
here and as I push this zoom up
nothing's happen happening on screen
that's because I'm not actually looking
at this clip that I have selected so if
I drag this over now we can see that
that Zoom is actually working to reset
any property you can click this little
circle Arrow or you can double click on
its
name and if I close the inspector I have
my two viewers again and I can open up
my media pool and my Effects by just
clicking on these buttons here any panel
that you want to resize a little bit
there's usually some little button like
this this shrink an expand
button that'll make the media pool go
smaller or bigger same thing for the
inspector we have kind of a similar way
to do things now you can't take any of
these panels and move them around they
always stay where they're at so you can
expand them or contract them but you
can't like make your own detailed layout
like you can in some other programs and
that's just something to get used to I
actually kind of like it this way
because I tend not to lose panels I
don't have them on three different tabs
and you know halfway onto my other
monitor and stuff it's always in the
same place so once you get used to where
it is it's actually pretty convenient to
have them always in the same place it's
like you know place for everything and
everything in its place I love that one
other thing to mention is right here in
kind of the middle right we have our
volume controls and when I'm scrubbing
through things you'll often see me just
click this
mute and that's just to mute the audio
monitoring and this isn't going to mute
it for my movie If I turn this volume up
or down it's not going to adjust the the
actual output volume of my movie it's
just how loud it's playing back on my
system so how loud it is on my
headphones or my speakers so if I turn
this all the way down and then I export
this you'll still hear all of the audio
if I have this muted you'll still hear
all the audio it's just a quick way to
kind of adjust the levels so they don't
blast your eard drums while you're
scrubbing right one other thing to note
before we move on here in kind of the
middle left there's this little button
and these are our timeline view options
and these be really convenient if you
want to change the way the tracks are
displayed or change whether you see
waveforms or not that's kind of where
that
happens and how those are
displayed whether you see thumbnails on
your video
tracks whether you have subtitle tracks
or
not all of that stuff lives in the
timeline view options right there and I
think that should cover most of the
things that you need to know to be
dangerous in the edit page as far as the
interface now let's get to actually
making an edit ourselves to do that
let's open up our media pool here and
under bin 2 we have a timeline called
edit page start if you want to get these
work files there is a link in the
description below and you can download
this media and project and follow along
with me so I'll just open this up just
by double clicking on a timeline if you
want to make a new timeline you can
rightclick anywhere here in the media
pool and go to timelines create create
new timeline there you can set your
timeline name and your settings and all
of that stuff if you untick use project
settings then you can select the format
resolution frame rate all that kind of
stuff most of the time you can just say
empty timeline and use project settings
and hit create and that's really all I
did for the edit page start timeline now
let's say we want to add a piece of
media I'm going to go over to our media
here and double click on edit media and
I'll also go over and close our
inspector so that we have our two View
here and let's just double click on a
piece of media to load it here in the
source viewer I can scrub through and
find the piece that I want and I can
play this back using these transport
controls here or I can use J on the
keyboard to play backwards k to stop and
L to play forward so I can just hit L on
the keyboard turn on our sound
here
fine
okay go check it out
roll it again okay let's find the tank
that we like here go check it
out no way you go check it
out
fine okay I'll check it out all right so
that's a good take so let's say that I
want to use this clip to actually work
with it and put it in our movie we're
going to have to put it in the timeline
so I can you can do that a few different
ways probably the simplest way is just
to grab the image here and just drag it
down into the timeline and then we're
going to make a clip here in the
timeline and from there I can trim this
and adjust this here in the timeline I
can also just use the video if I drag
using this little film strip or just the
audio if I grab this little waveform
icon and I can grab those separately
select both of these and delete them and
I can also click one of these buttons
right here these are different ways you
put the clip into the timeline
insert overwrite and replace for now
we'll just hit insert and that'll put
that clip there in the timeline and I
can zoom this to fit by hitting shift Z
that's just going to zoom out so I can
see everything in my timeline here and
now I can scrub through this and play it
back go check it out and see which parts
I like I don't want this entire clip I
want to just use part of it so to
shorten this I can Mouse over either the
beginning or the end of the clip and my
mouse cursor will turn into this little
left bracket if I grab this I can bring
it in and I'm shortening the clip here
I'm actually trimming off the beginning
of it I can trim that right before they
start talking can move my play head back
and hit space bar go check it
out no way you go check it out and
that's working but I think I actually
want this second take here
it's nothing we emerge with the crab
walk that you were talking about earlier
two
one
action go check it
out all
right so we'll start this right after he
says action just grab this and trim it
here go check it
out no way you go check it out
fine okay okay let's just stop it there
I'll take the end and trim this up to
the playhead and now we have just this
piece of our footage on our
timeline go check it
out one thing is that the audio is just
coming out of the left ear which we can
fix uh variety of ways but the reason is
this is a mono recording and we're
putting this into a stereo track so if I
right click here on this track header
and go down to change track type to and
select
mono then no way you go check it out
problem solved now something to mention
when you play this back it's going to
start at zero and look at this this is
way far down there so we always want to
take our footage and bring it all the
way to the
left because we play from left to right
if we have a gap like this we can select
the this empty part and hit backspace on
the keyboard to shrink this up here and
make sure that we start with this clip
now let's find another clip here double
click on this next one and we have
Gwen's angle
here take three go check it
out um no you go check it out all right
that's great that's really the part that
we want but we don't have to drag this
into the time line to select that part
we can actually select the part right
here before we even put it in the
timeline so for our selection we're
going to have that start right about
when she turns her head there and we're
just going to grab a little clip from
this piece of footage we're going to set
the starting point which is called an in
by hitting I on the keyboard you can
also hit this button right here this
Mark in and now we have this little kind
of brighter gray bar that shows up here
and let's scrub through
until this is totally done and then
we'll hit o for out again you can hit
this Mark out button like that and now
we have just a portion of this selected
when we have our in andout selected we
can grab this in the exact same way and
drag it down into the timeline but we're
only going to grab that little piece so
it's a little bit more efficient to do
that you don't have to drag the whole
thing into the timeline and then cut it
up and let's put this where it's
supposed to
be go check it out
no way you go check it
out and so really we want to cut to that
line as she says it so one thing we
could easily do is just grab this clip
and just drop it right here where it's
supposed to go and that's going to split
this original clip and cut to the one
that we just
added um no you go check it
out fine so because she says the same
line and does y the same movement that
edit actually works pretty well let's
actually take this back a couple steps
though I'll just hit contrl z a couple
times here during her line we could put
this directly over this clip right here
from The Source viewer we can even hit
this button over right clip and that's
going to put this clip down starting
right at the playhead so if I do this
it's going to do the same thing it's
going to overwrite the clip right at the
playhead so that's an easy way to kind
of switch things out depending on your
for preference you might want to put
this other clip in a second track and
all you do is just pull this up like
that and put this video layer on top of
the other video layer now as we play
this back you're only going to see the
top video layer right so it's the same
thing essentially as we did before we're
cutting to this angle instead but the
audio is going to mix so we're going to
hear the old line as well as the new
line here when we play this back um no
you go check it out which we don't want
to do do so we have a couple options we
can either just replace it like this or
we could do something like mute this
track if we only want to hear this
second track um no you go check it out
or we could even disable the clip if you
select any clip and hit D on the
keyboard that will disable it and by
default if you click on a clip it's
going to select the audio and the video
so we don't want the video disabled
right because we won't be able to see
the video so what we can do is select
the audio and the video separately and
we can do that a couple ways one way
would be just to unclick this little
link button right here and now if we
select the audio and the video we can
select those separately so I could
select this audio and hit D to disable
that the other way I could do this is
just keep this linked because I like to
have this linked because it's easy to
grab a clip and move it back and forth
but you can hold down alt and select
either the audio track or the video
track by itself without having to go and
unlink the selection that kind of thing
so that way we can turn this off now we
don't really want to turn the entire
thing off because we still want to hear
the lines in this clip so one thing we
can do is split this clip and disable
just this part and enable the other
parts so we can split this by going up
here to our tools and grabbing this
blade so this will turn your mouse
cursor into a razor blade and wherever
you click it's going to split that clip
in two so we can make a cut on either
side of this clip like this I can switch
back to my regular mode and then hit D
hold down alt to select just this audio
and hit D and now if we play this back
check it
out um no you go check it
out
fine and now we're doing some fancy
stuff this is really cool so depending
on your preference or you know how you
recorded your audio or how you want to
organize your Clips down here in the
tracks there's a lot of different ways
to adjust this something to mention too
when we are creating a story we're in
control of not only the clips that we
use but also how long each of those
clips lasts so there's nothing saying
that this clip go check it out and this
clip have to be spaced this far apart
from each other so that they're in real
time we can actually use this
opportunity of cutting to a different
clip to sort of compress the time here
and so he's kind of looking at things
now we could him look all the way back
and before he talks we can just get rid
of all of that
stuff and make this a little bit shorter
let's go check it
out um no you go check it out fine so
that makes that moment a little bit
shorter same thing here go check it
out we'll just make this a little
shorter select this emptiness bring it
up go check it out um no you go check it
out fine so we're in control of the
pacing we can also make this paste a
little bit
longer so we could take this and run it
out a little bit like
this go check it
out um no you go check it out so that
way she pauses for a lot longer now most
of the time you want it to just feel
natural right so go check it
out so she thinks for just a
second and right as she kind of starts
to turn her head
here that's where we'll cut in select
all of those and just roll them back
select this empty space and move it up
check it
out um no you go check it
out fine the other thing we like to do
is when there's an action like her
pushing him it's nice to cut on that
action and so if we kind of bring this
up where she pushes him like
this we could cut right in the middle of
that push so right as she's pushing him
like
that and it kind of follows through she
starts pushing in this shot and hands up
moving through that shot you go check it
out and it feels a lot more natural even
though this was shot maybe an hour after
this shot feels like it's all the same
moment um no you go check it
out fine and so that's really how you
build a story here in the edit page now
a couple of shortcuts that I think are
really helpful let's say we want to cut
into this shot all the way up to here
there are a couple different things that
we could do to get rid of this first
part we could just grab the edge of it
and trim it up like this and then delete
that empty space to move it
up we could also split the clip right
here with our
razor and then select this part and hit
backspace select the empty space and hit
backspace we could split it here select
this clip and hit delete that's like the
smaller backspace the smaller delete
button above the numbers on a lot of
keyboards and that will get rid of the
empty space as well Allin one Fell Swoop
but we can make this even faster than
that one thing we can do is use a
keyboard shortcut to cut our clip you
can hit contrl B on the keyboard to
Blade clips under the play
head and so I could come over here hit
contrl B select this and hit delete and
that goes a little bit faster you can
also at this point without even cutting
it you could hit control shift left
bracket and what that's going to do is
trim this all the way up to here and get
rid of that empty space all at once once
so here it goes boom and so that I think
is the easiest way to trim things that
are just lined out on the timeline like
this um no you go check it out
fine so this is a little bit tight so
check it
out I like when she pushes him oh check
it
out get out
fine and that's really how you start to
build your story so let's go ahead and
work through an edit here and I'll show
you a really easy way to get a basic
story lined out in your
timeline I'm just going to go to my
footage anything that I know that is in
this scene and just double click on it
and we're going to start by kind of
scrubbing through it seeing what happens
so this is the wide shot of him
approaching the craft so I'm just going
to roughly hit an an in
in and an out like that and just drag
this into the timeline doesn't matter
where we're just throwing it in here
because we're going to work with it here
in a few minutes next clip this is the
shot of them looking at the craft so I'm
using JK andl to kind of page through
this and we're going to start right
before they step
in there we go and we crane up like
this and let's hit o for out out then
it's a matter of does this happen before
or after this clip it happens before and
so I can move my playhead before the
clip and then this first icon this
insert clip I can insert it and it will
put it there in the timeline before my
first clip so that happens before it in
pretend land right next let's go to this
clip
here great that goes in between these
two clips so I'll just hit in
insert next this is going to go during
that clip again I'll probably just use
that override idea just put this right
over her
line there we go next
clip go check it
out go check it out all right so this is
an Al angle and I don't have to make a
bunch of decisions right now I could
probably just insert this for now and
we'll work on this later but I'm just
getting all the media that I want into
the timeline so this is kind of the
beginning and I'm just picking the tank
that I want great this is going to go
before everything else I'll hit shift Z2
back up we'll go all the way to the
beginning insert that go to the next so
this is her looking on as he he walks
forward we'll
just and this is going to go somewhere
in there not really even sure where but
I'll just throw that in it's okay you
don't have to know everything right off
the bat here's another angle of him
walking up there we go and we'll throw
this in there
too I can hit L multiple times to play
at Double speed or even four or 8X speed
to kind of scrub through this really
quickly so again I'll put this somewhere
in here I'll just insert it
there here's a closeup of
him good it's going to go somewhere in
there
also then we have the over the shoulder
shot
go great and we'll put this in there
somewhere too so now I have all of my
footage thrown in here in roughly the
order that I want I can close my media
pool because I don't really need that
anymore and now it's a matter of going
through and making these kind of make
sense in the story so we can start at
the beginning
and one thing that might be helpful is
to grab the divider here between the
audio and the video tracks and you can
kind of push this up and you can take
the divider between the audio tracks and
push this down and you can see a lot
bigger waveforms here CU a lot of the
time you're going to edit around sounds
that happen in dialogue and that kind of
thing so it's nice to really see clearly
where those
are okay they say whoo and then what do
they see I'm just going to chop the edge
off of this with control shift right
bracket and let's get rid of this empty
space here what do they
see I think we'll just bring it in right
about there I'll hit control shift left
bracket to chop the front off of that
let kind of goes up like
that same thing I'll cut off the end so
what do they
see yeah they see that whoa now their
reaction let's let him just think about
it for a little
bit go check it
out um no you go check it out now to get
really detailed here we can zoom in if I
hold alt and roll up with my scroll
wheel on my mouse I can zoom way in you
can also move this slider right here to
zoom in or out on the
playhead okay so she looks kind of that
way trim that off what one thing that
can sometimes be helpful is to uncheck
this magnet this is turns on our
snapping snapping is when if you get
close to the edge of a clip your
playhead kind of jumps to the edge of
that clip and also if you're moving
Clips around they kind of snap together
like that if you turn this
off then it doesn't really snap to
anything you can be a little bit more
precise so let's take a look at this so
she's already looking that way and we'll
just trim it like
this um no you go check it out
go check it
out um no you go check it
out okay now we have this reaction from
him which I like that we don't need the
other
parts
fine
okay I'll go check it
out let's cut after
okay
okay fine so maybe right as
she pushes him and then he looks back
that
way maybe we'll cut on
that fine we could cut right on that
move if we wanted
to and now we can take these clips and
swap them actually if I hold control
shift and then less than I can move this
clip and kind of swap it with other
Clips so let's just see how this works
you go check it
out fine
this clip is a little bit short so we
can take this and extend it a little bit
oh you go check it
out
fine
okay
fine okay I'll check it I'll check it
out so we could cut to him right there
okay I'll check it
out bring a little bit more time there
okay I'll check it out could also cut to
the other angle check it
out I like that a little better I think
that's a better
angle okay Che it
out and now he approaches the ship right
and so this is really where it comes
down to personal preference how do you
want to tell the story what Clips do you
want to use what order should they be in
how long should each of them be what's
the pacing in between the clips and so
let's go ahead and jump to the edit page
finished timeline and this is what we
ended up doing for the actual
movie w
w go check it
out um no you go check it
out
fine
okay check it
out and so we have these other shots
mixed in we have her looking on we have
a shot of him approaching the ship his
reaction her reaction all of this just
mixed into one moment now something to
mention is that the audio isn't super
great here this is just what we would do
if we were to line things out in the
edit page before we render this we would
want to clean up the audio add some
footsteps add some sound effects and all
of that stuff make sure that the voices
sound level and all of that stuff which
some of that we can do in the edit page
but we're mostly going to worry about
that in Fair light in this course now
let's talk about how to get a little bit
more detailed any of these clips in the
timeline if we want to adjust some of
the details about them we just select it
and then we can go up here to the upper
right and click inspector now this is
where all of the properties live for
something that's in the timeline and
generally anywhere in resolve if you
have something selected and you go to
the inspector you can adjust the
properties for it okay so just kind of
get used to that I'm going to make this
a little bit bigger here so I'll just
select this footage and starting in this
upper part we have our transform so
transform is is like moving things
around turning them rotating them
positioning them that kind of thing
zooming them in so we can zoom stuff in
we can change its position we can change
its rotation angle we can even do pitch
and yaw which kind of does sort of like
a 3D transform is looking thing like
a which can be useful sometimes we can
also flip this on the vertical axis and
the horizontal axis this is the kind of
stuff that you're going to use a lot
also in the lower left hand corner of
our viewer there's this little transform
button and if you click on that and it
turns white you can actually grab the
image and move it around here in the
viewer you can grab this little handle
to rotate it you can grab the corners to
scale it and move it around and that's
really helpful too but this is the same
kind of controls as our transform in
fact if you move this around you can see
our
position moving around as we move
it you can reset any of these controls
with this little circle Arrow you can do
single control like this or all of them
for the group here with this circle with
a
plus to turn off this overlay you just
click on that button again and now you
can't move things around we also have
quite a bit of other controls including
cropping so we can crop this footage the
Left Right top or bottom when we have
this cropped we can also adjust the
softness of the crop great for a lot of
situations we have a dynamic zoom and
this is really cool this will actually
take a shot and it will Zoom it out
throughout the duration of the shot you
can also swap it to zoom it
in throughout the duration of the shot
that works really well and you have some
options for
easing this is really great if you're
doing something like a slideshow or if
you want to just make your edit a little
bit more Dynamic you can even just
select multiple different clips here in
the timeline and if you have multiple
clips selected you can adjust the
properties common to all of the clips
and so I could just turn on Dynamic Zoom
for everything and now look what happens
this is zooming
out on every shot which may or may not
be what we actually want for this kind
of thing it's actually not a good idea
but for something if you have kind of a
high action edit where it's nice to have
those kind of dynamic
moves that can be really helpful now we
don't want to do it for this let's not
dynamically Zoom every single shot we
also have composite mode and opacity for
each shot so we can turn the opacity
down we can change the composite mode if
it's over something else we'll actually
be able to see that so I can switch that
to add that's going to mix these
together depending on what you want to
do and these are just like composite
modes in any other kind of layer based
program and there's also some more
advanced things like stabilization lens
correction that kind of thing as well as
retiming and scaling controls you have a
lot of control over the visual aspects
of whatever clip you have selected here
in the inspector but up at the top there
are some other tabs here if we click on
audio this is where we can adjust the
volume and the pan the pitch and even
our equalizer for whatever clip we have
selected and we can get really detailed
with our audio even just here in the
edit page so even if you don't want to
jump into Fair light later you have
quite a bit of control over how loud
your Clips are and what they sound like
and all of that so some of this audio
stuff we're going to get into in Fair
light and it works in a very similar way
but if you do want to adjust audio here
in the edit page here's where you can do
it you can even just click on this track
header and you have a little bit of
control over your volume for your track
here in the edit page you can also go to
the mixer and do a little bit of
adjustment of track volume as well as a
little bit of panning here in the mixer
now let's say we want to start getting
fancy here in the edit page in the upper
leth hand corner I can open up my
effects panel that's going to open up
kind of under my media pool I'll just
close my media pool so we have lots of
room
and this is where we have all kinds of
different things that we can do to our
Clips in our edit page as well as some
fancy stuff that we can add to our edit
here so probably one of the more obvious
uses would be to actually put an effect
on here now ironically a lot of the
effects that you might want something
like a blur or something like that isn't
really under effects this is really
where a lot of the fusion based effects
live but if you go to open effects then
you'll find a lot of the filters and
things that you're used to things like
blur
box blur lens blur some color effects
some ke and kind of green screen ability
things things like ways to add lens
flares and glows and lens Reflections
and light rays and all kinds of cool
stuff this is where all of that lives
here in the effects panel under open
effects and so you can go through and
play around with these there are quite a
bit of effects that I have here that you
might not have in the free version that
is one of the limitations of the free
version but there are still quite a bit
of really cool effects in the free
version just not quite as many there are
some really cool ones that are only in
the paid version of resolve now to apply
an effect let's just put a blur on this
I'll just take this lens blur and we can
double click on it and that'll add that
to whatever clip that we have selected
and then if we select the clip and go
over to the inspector we have a new tab
here that's available effects and under
open effects here we have all of our
adjustments for this effect so we can
adjust the
size how bright the highlights are and
all of that kind of stuff and so again
when you have the clip
selected you can adjust the properties
of the effects that you have on the clip
right here in the effects tab here in
the
inspector to get rid of an effect you
can just click the garbage can like that
let's say we want to add some text or
some kind of title over this over here
in the effects panel we have several
different categories here we've been
playing with open effects we also have
audio effects by the way which we'll get
into later but under our toolbox we have
something called titles and under titles
here at the top we have our basic text
and we can grab basic text and this time
instead of putting it on a clip like
this we can drag it over the clip just
like we were dragging a piece of media
from the media pool onto the timeline
when you drag a title or a generator
here into the timeline it's like it
creates a new piece of footage and so
now I have this title and I can adjust
this on the timeline just like I would a
clip
and I can select it and adjust its
properties just like I would a clip but
you know its properties for this title
are something like some text and we can
adjust the font and the size and the
tracking and all these kind of things
that you would expect to be able to
adjust here with the text generator and
so again grab this play around with it
there's actually quite a bit of cool
stuff that you can do just with this
basic
text and of course we have preset titles
for you know lower thirds
as well as like scrolling credits that
scroll from the bottom and again select
it and go over here to the inspector to
adjust its
properties under generators we have
things that aren't really titles but you
know ways to generate like a solid color
ways to generate a gradient ways to
generate color bars that kind of thing
just in the edit page of resolve you
have just about everything that you need
to be able to create a video in fact you
could even go up to workspace and just
turn off show page navigation right here
and you have everything that you need
right here this is basically like a
program like Final Cut or Premiere this
is everything that you need to be able
to preview and select your footage bring
it into the timeline create a story and
get detailed with the properties of all
of your clips and mix them together and
adjust the audio and apply effects and
all of that kind of thing really the
only thing you can't do super well in
the edit page is color grade and that's
because the color page is just so
fantastic and resolve started with color
and so you know there wasn't really a
big need to make a robust color effect
here in the edit page but I would say
like 90% of what you need to do in
resolve you could probably do in the
edit page if you're just making a basic
video and you're not trying to get into
super detailed Motion Graphics or visual
effects or compositing or that kind of
thing the edit page is sort of like your
hub for your story and from here we can
go out to the other Pages I'll just
bring these back up and get more
detailed if you're looking for more
resources on how to edit videos well in
D Vinci resolve make sure to check out
this right here that's our D Vinci
resolve resources guide It's a PDF with
the best resources that we found for
learning to edit in D Vinci resolve and
you can get that for free all you have
to do is click on that card there's also
a link in the description let's keep
going before we get into those next
three pages we're going to jump on over
to the cut page
the cut page we're not going to spend
quite as much time on because it
essentially does a similar thing to the
edit page in fact a lot of editors that
I talk to uh they don't really use the
cut page very much and it's too bad
because the cut page is really cool so
that begs the question what's so cool
about a page that does basically the
same thing as the edit page and why are
there two pages that do almost the same
thing well the edit page is designed for
what we've been talking about you know
putting everything together for your
story you can get pretty detailed with
stuff you can add effects and stack
clips and all of that stuff to make a
really complicated timeline I mean you
can make a feature film you can make
television shows with multiple cameras
and all this crazy stuff here in the
edit page but the cut page is designed
for a certain kind of project certain
kind of workflow it's designed to take a
lot of the editing stuff that you would
do in the edit page and kind of
streamline it and make it easier and
faster to put a story together really
really quickly and you'll notice the
layout is sort of similar to the edit
page here in the upper left we have our
media pool and this is sort of a strip
down version of the media pool with some
things moved around but it's still
essentially the media pool it's where
the media that is imported into our
project lives and then on the right we
have our viewer now we don't have two
viewers here like we do in the edit page
when our inspector is closed anyway
where we have our source viewer and our
timeline
viewer we just have one viewer and this
is kind of a hybrid
if you double click on a piece of
footage here in the media pool you can
bring it up here in the viewer and
preview it but if you click down in the
timeline it's going to switch to the
timeline viewer and you'll be able to
view your timeline now speaking of the
timeline there's actually two different
views of the timeline there's the lower
timeline here which by default moves
under the playhead and the playhead kind
of stays stationary in the middle and
then there's the upper timeline where
you can move the playhead around it's
designed this way so that you don't have
to zoom in and out all the time so like
in edit I can hold alt and zoom in and
out and if I want to see the end of my
movie I zoom out and then I can zoom
back in I'm just holding alt and rolling
with the scroll wheel and you know it's
pretty fast but you do kind of have to
move things around and there's a lot of
moving back and forth and reframing so
that you can see what you're doing well
the cut page is always zoomed out in the
upper timeline you can see the very
beginning and the Very end of your
sequence in this upper timeline and the
bottom is always zoomed in and so you
can quickly go to the very last clip
just by clicking over here on the right
part of your upper timeline and then you
can adjust the details and stuff here in
the lower part of your timeline without
having to zoom in and out to do that
right so you can quickly kind of go
through this and trim things and make
adjustments whatever you need right here
in the lower timeline and switch to a
different part in the upper timeline and
it's kind kind of just designed to go
really quickly but other than that
layout you have a lot of the same
controls in the cut page as you do in
the edit page it's just sort of
streamlined a little bit so for instance
this viewer where we have our transform
controls where we can kind of turn this
on and move it around and that kind of
thing and we have the inspector as kind
of these separate controls here in the
edit
page in the cut
page we can just click on these sliders
and we have all of that all kind of in
one little panel here
and so our transform we can move this
around and adjust and they're all kind
of next to each other and so it's just a
little bit quicker to move things around
same thing for
cropping and so it's just kind of
designed to be a little bit more
streamlined right that said I think
people kind of complained about not
having the inspector because they
recently added the inspector here on the
right and you can kind of do similar
things that you would in the edit
page I'll just reset all my controls
with this little ccle plus right here
and something to mention about the cut
page not only do we have these timelines
but by default these timelines are kind
of designed to not let you have a gap
between your Clips so I don't have
separate tools for my cursor like I do
here in the edit page where you can grab
different tools grab your blade tool
grab your regular selection tool grab
your trim tool in the cut page you just
Mouse over the edge of a clip and you
have one option you kind of trim the
clip and the other Clips suck down with
it and that's just designed to make it
so you don't have any gaps in your
timeline because we don't want any black
frames or anything like that we just
want all of the clips to play next to
each other now there are times where you
actually do want a gap and you can
change that option along with a bunch of
other options here in this very leand
part of this upper timeline there are a
lot of different options here this top
one is called Ripple on if we uncheck
that we can move it like this and it
won't Ripple the other Clips down so
that's called Rippling kind of moving
things down when you trim things so it
will let you have those gaps if you want
to have
those one of the things we like about
the cut page is just being able to
quickly go through and trim your clips
now this does get a little bit
frustrating when you have your audio
offset a little bit like mine is here I
have this clip's audio coming in before
the video and if ever to grab this it's
somewhat unpredictable uh what's going
to happen here and so it's keeping those
same edit points but it's moving
everything down which may or may not be
what you want and so I find that you
generally want to use the cut page for
things where you have straight cuts you
want to have a bunch of Clips with
straight cuts like this because the more
you do this kind of Ripple thing the
more it's going to kind of mess it up so
this is really a great way to do
something where you have a bunch of
Clips just laid out right after one
another something something like a vlog
something like a news story where you
just don't have a whole bunch of fancy
audio and stuff like that that's really
where the cut page gets kind of
confusing and frustrating is when you
have a bunch of audio that you're trying
to kind of layer in and do j cuts and L
Cuts you know especially when you have
multiple tracks of audio and that kind
of thing it can get a little bit
confusing in the cut page and so the cut
page is something that I've really used
for things like Vlogs things like if I
have a vacation video where I just have
a ton of clips and I just play them one
after another another I can drag them
all into the cut page and really quickly
kind of trim them up and put them
together that way and what's beautiful
is you can actually use the cut page for
the things that it's fast at like you
know putting together a rough cut or
putting together a simple video like
that and then if you want to get a
little bit more detailed you can just
switch over to the edit page and this
uses the same timeline so the edit page
and the cut page and actually all of the
pages in resolve share the same timeline
which is one of the major advantages of
resolve being the way it is so we can do
some work in the cut page and then go to
the edit page to get more detailed and
that kind of thing it's a pretty decent
overview of the cut page let's take a
look at a couple strengths that the cut
page really has and some reasons why you
might want to jump into the cut page
even if you're not going to stay there
for the entirety of your project one
feature that I really like about the cut
page is the source tape so if you go up
in the upper lefthand corner of our
viewer here you have these three buttons
and this switches out your viewer
between the source clip so like a clip
from your media pool and your timeline
so whatever you have down here so we'll
just throw a couple things down here
real
quick but this middle button is the
source tape button and look what happens
when I click this what this will do is
this will take all of the media from
whatever bin I'm looking at in my media
pool and it will lay it out end to end
here in our little play
bar and then I can scrub through this
and I can look at all of my media in one
smooth motion and so this is really
great if you're trying to find a piece
of media and you don't know what it's
called instead of double clicking on a
piece of media and then scrubbing
through it and then double clicking on
another piece of media and scrubbing
through it with the source tape you can
just scrub through all of your media all
at once this is especi good if you're
trying to find a shot visually finding
some Boll something like that and so
what I do is I use this to find Boll for
projects where you know I might have a
voice over and I'm trying to put Boll
over it just to accentuate what's being
said you can really quickly kind of buzz
through your footage and find the right
clip and you can set your in and your
out just like you would on the edit page
like this with I and O and then you can
take this and you can put it into the
timeline now you can put this into the
the timeline a few different ways one
you could just drag it into the timeline
like you would expect but we also have
these buttons over here these are the
edit buttons and whatever we have
selected with our in andout here in the
viewer this will throw into the timeline
in various different ways one that makes
a lot of sense would be place on top and
so we click place on top and it's going
to put that clip on top of our other
Clips here right wherever our playhead
is so if our play head's over here and I
hit place on top it's going to put that
on top right there
we also have Ripple overr right so let's
say I pick an alternate angle
here in out and then I say Ripple
overwrite what that's going to do is put
this clip into this space and it's going
to fit the space to the clip boom it's
going to kind of replace that clip right
there and that can be really convenient
if you're just trying to quickly replace
a
shot another convenient one would be
smart insert so let's say I want to put
this in between these two Clips I don't
even have to be right on this edit point
I just have to have that edit point be
the nearest edit point to my playhead
and I can hit smart insert and look what
happens boom it puts that in between
those two clips and so all of these are
kind of designed to save you a little
bit of time so you don't have to be
exactly right with your playhead you
know you just make this as close as you
can set your in and you're out smart
insert and you can put that in there and
so this is really great for putting a
whole bunch of footage into the timeline
really quickly this kind of system
working with the cut page and these edit
buttons what I think is even nicer is
you can set keyboard shortcuts for any
of these buttons and so if you go up to
the upper leand corner under D Vinci
resolve under keyboard customization if
you click on all commands here you can
search so like append and that button is
the same as a pen to end of timeline and
I like to set this as P the reason I put
this as p is because it's right by I and
O on the keyboard and so I can go
through here and I can quickly add a
bunch of Clips like this I O and then
hit p and when I hit P it's going to
throw this clip at the end of my
timeline and so I can quickly just
gather all the clips that I want i o p i
o p i o p and if you're working with you
know more visual clips and b roll and
that kind of thing I O and P you can
throw all of your Boll at the end of
your timeline and then you can go
through here and put them over your
voice over and adjust things and get a
little bit more detailed
afterwards so a lot of the time what
I'll do is I'll be working on my edit
here in the edit page and then I'll
switch over to the cut page to use the
source tape to grab a bunch of b-roll
kind of buzz through my
clips and just put those on my edit and
once I have all the click Clips there
it's just a really fast way to go
through a bunch of Clips I can switch
back over to the edit page and I can
adjust my Clips here in the edit page
where I have a little bit more control
it really depends on your workflow and
the type of project you're doing but
this Source tape is a really nice tool
the other thing the cut page is really
good for is doing multi-cam edits Now
you kind of wouldn't think of the edit
page as being great at multi-cam because
it it kind of seems like this is a way
just to make rough cuts it doesn't quite
have as many abilities as the edit page
but let me show you something really
cool I'm going to go into our files here
under our media under our cut page media
and here we have a multicam shoot of the
read through of our movie so this is
five people around a table we have a top
down camera we have a kind of the left
side of the table camera and right side
of the table camera and in the edit page
you can make a multi-cam sequence and
you can flip cameras and do all that
kind of thing which is definitely plenty
to go over in its own video but the cut
page does kind of a unique thing with
multi-cam edits if we select all of this
stuff that are just different angles of
the same moment we can go up here to
this
button it says sync clips and if we
click on that that's going to bring up
our sync Clips
window and here we have some options to
be able to automat automatically sync
these clips together and make a multicam
edit if you have time code you can sync
by time code you can sync by the start
or the end of the clip the in and the
out or you can do it automatically with
audio and for most of us that's probably
what is going to be most useful so I'll
select audio and hit sync and look what
happens it analyzes it and then it puts
these all together and thinks about
where these all fit together in time at
this point it's a really good idea to
play this and make sure that the sync is
right but it usually does a really good
job and then you just go down here to
save
sync now it looks like nothing's
happened nothing's really going on here
but what it does is it adds these little
blue indicators which means that it
knows that these clips belong together
and that they occupy the same moment in
time and so what we can do is grab
something like our Master shot like this
wide shot I'll just right click and say
create new
timeline and I'll just drag this down to
our timeline here and now we have the
entire shoot from beginning to end just
with this one clip now this isn't a
multi-cam sequence or anything like that
it's just literally the clip thrown into
the timeline but we can go up here to
the upper left and go to something
called a sync bin and we can see all of
the clips that sync with the clip that
we're over here in the timeline and we
can see all the different cameras and
everything like that and check this out
we can play this back or or scrub
through or whatever we want to do and if
we find a good angle we can click on
that angle and that's going to bring
that up here in our viewer and it's
going to set an in at the point that's
going to sync with our
playhead and we could do something like
place on top and look at this it's going
to come in
here and if we switch off of our sync
bin we can see what's actually happening
here in our timeline as we play this
back this is going to be perfectly
synced and we can just add clips that we
think are interesting and we can do it
perfectly in sync without having to set
up a whole multicam sequence and switch
cameras and all of that kind of stuff
it's almost like a hybrid between
putting a bunch of clips into a timeline
and just editing them that way and a
traditional multi-cam workflow so this
sync bin is pretty cool switch over to
the sync bin again and this is how we
can do our multi-cam edit and it's just
kind of a slick way to do
it and so the sink bin is a really nice
way to be able to kind of scrub through
and find interesting stuff and just find
the best angle so let's just go to this
angle drop that
in and now we have a nice Dynamic edit
here that works really well and we
didn't really have to do a whole lot of
work sinking things up so if you're
doing multicam stuff the cut page might
actually be a really great tool for you
now something to mention about the cut
page the cut page is actually designed
to work with some hardware and so if you
don't know there is the D Vinci resolve
editor keyboard which is a whole
keyboard that has specialized buttons on
the left and in a jog wheel and some
other buttons here on the right and this
was kind of designed with the cut page
in mind and so it sort of brings some
more tactile control to your editing we
also have the speed editor which is like
the next generation of the editor
keyboard and this thing's pretty neat it
has your edit buttons right here as
dedicated keys on the keyboard your in
and out there's ways to trim and roll
and do your different edits and add
transitions as well as multi-cam
controls some other useful features
switching between the source and the
timeline viewers and then of course you
have your jog wheel which helps you kind
of navigate back and forth on the
timeline like I said this is kind of
designed for the cut page and so if you
are doing a certain kind of project
and you're doing a lot of it this speed
editor might be a really good idea
because it's more about kind of building
tactile control and muscle memory and
with some practice you can get really
fast editing things with this speed
editor and that's designed to work with
the cut page to where you don't have to
use a mouse and a keyboard you can just
use the speed editor and it does feel
really cool when you kind of get the
hang of it and this is also where the
cut page kind of starts to make a little
bit more sense you know using the speed
editor on the edit page feels like oh I
don't know this is kind of cool using
the cut page without the speed editor is
like oh yeah this is kind of neat but
when you use them together it really
makes a lot of sense and things feel
really nice so depending on how much
you're going to be editing and how
hardcore you're going to be and what
kind of projects you're going to be
working on the cut page and especially
with the speed editor might be a really
good idea so my advice is to open the
Cut page try it out see how you like it
if you are interested in buying the full
version of resolve that's the paid
version the studio version it actually
comes with the speed editor and so you
could buy that speed editor for 3.95 and
get resolve Studio which is $2.95 for
free with it and that's a pretty sweet
deal if you're into editing and you're
going to do a high volume of stuff would
definitely check out the speed editor
watch some reviews it's a pretty neat
little piece of equipment but that's
pretty much the editing side of things
here in resolve we we have the edit page
which is really kind of the Hub of your
project this is where you put your story
together this is where you add the
majority of your media and everything
anything that you want your viewer to
see you have to put into the timeline
the cut page is a little bit different
flavor of doing that and again if you're
just wanting to do some basic videos
it's totally okay to just stay on the
and work with the tools there but if you
want to take things up a notch that's
where these next three pages come in
you can think of the edit page and the
cut page as like level one kind of
putting things together the basics but
when you want to get a little bit more
advanced and you want to get more
detailed with either doing some visual
effects or making Graphics or doing
color correction or doing audio that's
where you would jump into fusion color
or Fair
light all right let's jump into Fusion
this is my favorite part of Da Vinci
resolve and I think probably the most
powerful thing in Da Vinci resolve as
far as creating anything that you can
imagine Fusion like the other pages is
like an entire app like an entire
different app shoved into resolve and
like all of these Pages it has one major
job Fusion's job is to be a compositor
so what is a compositor well a
compositor is an app where you do
compositing solid solid information
right compositing is combining different
visual elements together to make one
cohesive image and when you say
compositing that can be visual effects
which is like fancy stuff like
explosions and lightsabers and making
things that aren't real look real but it
can also be something like titles and
graphics and animations things that are
kind of computer generated it's all a
similar process of putting a bunch of
stuff together into one image one
composition what this might look like is
let's say you have a shot of a cow in a
field with mountains in the background
something you might do in compositing
would be to add more
Mountains that can be a copy of these
mountains or it can be Mountains from a
totally different place it could be some
image that was shot on the other side of
the world and we're just going to put
that in to our shot and make it look
real maybe we want the sky to look a
little bit fancier maybe we'll put some
clouds in the sky make it look a little
bit more like a story book these would
all be examples of visual effects it's
making something that isn't real look
real and they can be really realistic
like this where you really wouldn't even
notice if you did a good job or
something crazy like hey we have a
flying saucer that comes in and abducts
this cow all of this kind of stuff is
what Fusion does let's say we want to
have a title that comes in and animates
on and then a flying saucer comes in and
then grabs the title and then lifts it
off of screen that's more kind of the
motion graphic side of things
but you can sort of think of compositing
as doing stuff that's fancy to your
video so using the fusion page we can do
things like take this shot of the house
and turn this into a nighttime shot and
add fog and remove all of these trees
and take away this American flag and add
fake lighting and I mean you can do
anything you want if you have the skills
and learn how to do it Fusion can
probably do just about anything that you
imagine so it's really exciting because
this is built into resolve and what's
neat is that you can take any clip from
any timeline and to bring it into Fusion
you don't need to convert it or you
don't need to link it out to any other
kind of program or render it or anything
like that all you do is just look at the
shot in the edit page and then switch
over to fusion and it brings up that
shot here in the fusion page and you can
play with it and do all the fancy things
pretty neat right so enough of what
Fusion does how do we actually do
anything well let's take a look at the
interface here there should be some
things that are familiar by now in the
upper left hand corner we have our media
pool and this works just like in the
other Pages it's all of the media that's
been imported into our project in fact
let me go up to workspace and reset our
UI layout there we go it's possible the
your screen looks a little bit more like
this and of course in the upper left we
have these buttons up here and this
opens and closes panels just like in the
edit page same thing media pool and
effects both live over here on the left
side on the right side we have our
inspector and we have some other panels
that we can open and close that we'll
get to here in a little bit over here on
the right we have our viewer and
actually we have two viewers here in
Fusion a left-hand viewer and a
right-hand viewer and for now you can
think of this sort of like the source
viewer and the timeline viewer although
that's not exact right but for now you
can totally think about it like that cuz
I have to explain a couple things before
this will make any sense why there's two
viewers but just so you know there's two
viewers a left viewer and a right viewer
and by default if you play through the
timeline what you see on the right is
what your image is going to look like
when it goes back into the edit page now
in the lower part of our interface we
have the nodes now this strikes fear
into the hearts of many nodes are
probably the most single intimidating
reason why people don't want to use
Fusion because they see this kind of
interface they see a couple boxes
connected to each other and they go what
the heck is that why is that this makes
no sense how can something that's time
based not have a timeline with layers
like the edit page does there's a
timeline with layers I get that what's
with the fusion page with these boxes
what are we supposed to do with that
well if you're thinking that way then
you're not alone it's okay the very
first time you see nodes it's it's kind
of weird so let's let's take a minute
and let's explain what the heck nodes
are because they're really the key to
working infusion they're like the main
thing that you use to make cool stuff
infusion so what is a node a node is
just a little box on our interface and
we link these boxes up like a flowchart
each box has at least one input and it
has an output the output is this little
gray square and every input is a
triangle and there are different colored
triangles every single node has
basically one job it kind of does one
thing you can think of a node as like a
single step in a process at Ground
Control we have a program called Fusion
Zero to Hero which teaches you all of
the ins and outs in Fusion we go super
deep into all the concepts that you need
to know and one of the first things that
we do to help people understand nodes is
we explain it like a recipe here's some
homework from one of our students where
they had to make a flowchart for for a
recipe and so this is just how to make
pizza right so you get the dough you
roll the dough out you get some sauce
you put the sauce on the dough you get
some cheese you add the cheese you get
the toppings you add the toppings you
bake and then at the end you have pizza
and you'll notice each of these
nodes is like one action one action is
get the dough one action is roll the
dough one action is get the sauce right
and they all connect together pretty
much from left to right and you put all
of the steps in order and by the end you
have something
tasty here's another one I really like
about making ramen so you get the bowl
you get some flour you sift the flour
you pour the flour into the bowl you get
some water you mix the water with the
flour you knead it you pull it and then
you have Ramen and this is really all a
node chart is is putting a bunch of
steps in a certain
order the difference is instead of
making food we're changing our shot so
if we want to make our shot foggy we can
start with a house shot we can take some
fog and we can put the fog over the
house then we can color correct it we
could zoom it in and then at the end
it's connected to a media out which is
what gets sent to the
timeline so really all we're doing with
nodes is we're making a flowchart and by
default if you open up a shot from the
timeline you have a very simple
flowchart you have media in and media
out and each node has one job media in's
job is to grab a video from the timeline
and bring it here into Fusion media
out's job is to take whatever we connect
to that yellow input and put that back
into the edit page everything fancy kind
of happens in between media in and media
out so if we were to take something like
a blur node which by the way this little
bar here this is our toolbar but it
doesn't change our cursor it actually is
just a quick way to make a node you can
just drag any of these icons down and it
will create a new
node and so we could take this blur icon
and drag that down in between media in
and media out and when this little
connection turns blue we can drop this
on the connection and look it's
connected in between these two nodes
then we can select the blur and again
anything that we have selected we can
adjust in the inspector kind of the same
way it works in the edit page and as I
push this blur size up it blurs the
image so really if you can do this then
that's essentially how nodes work and
now we have a blurry image and if we go
back to the edit page guess what our
image is blurry here in the edit page
because this is using the output of
fusion to make this video
clip of course we can do a lot more
fancy things than just blur things so
let's switch back to Fusion let's get
rid of that blur
and let's talk about some of the major
nodes that you're going to work with if
you're going to make cool things in
Fusion so there are hundreds of nodes in
Fusion if you go over to the effects
panel under Tools each one of these is a
node oh my goodness how are we ever
going to survive so many nodes here's
the good news you don't really need to
know most of these you could just go
ahead and close this effects panel right
there a lot of the nodes that you're
actually going to use are right here on
the
toolbar and they have dividers that sort
of break these up into categories
because there's really only four
different types of nodes there are kind
of some extra ones but there's like four
main types and the first you might call
an image node for instance media in
would be an image node and remember I
said that we'd get back to these two
viewers well you can actually view any
node itself in either of these viewers
just by grabbing the node and dragging
it into the viewer you can also hit one
or two on the
keyboard to toggle its view in either of
the
viewers you can also click these little
dots you probably have two dots I have
three dots because I have an external
monitor with a special Blackmagic card
but don't worry about it mostly you're
only going to worry about these first
two dots if it's white it's in the
viewer if it's black it's not in the
viewer and so when you Mouse over things
we can say media out is in the second
viewer and media in is in the first
viewer now this is great because you can
look at any node by itself instead of
just what happens at the end and you can
kind of isolate different parts of your
node graph but more on that in a minute
so media in one this is an image node
that means that its main job is to
display an image for media in that's
usually a image from the timeline or
from the media
pool and so if I were to grab a piece of
footage here in the media pool I can
drag this down into the node graph and
that makes another media in node so all
this does is just like play footage it
displays images right another node that
I would put in this category would be
nodes that generate images so for
instance a background node this is one
that you're going to use all the time
all it does if I take this and drag this
in is it creates a solid color color you
can select this and go over to the
inspector and change the color right so
if we have this kind of dark red all it
does is make an image that's just a
solid red color and it can actually
create a bunch of different kinds of
backgrounds including like a four corner
gradient and you can do all kinds of
fancy stuff with a background node but
by default it's just a solid color so
even though we're creating this solid
color here and we're importing an image
here really what's happening is we're
making an image exist in Fusion same
thing for this second node here fast
noise what this does if I hit one on the
keyboard is it generates clouds and
again I can go over to the inspector and
adjust like the detail and the scale and
we can see it's just making clouds so
it's creating an image same thing for a
text node I can take this node here drag
it to the first viewer and I can type
some text and even though we're making
text what we're really doing is we're
generating an image of this text we're
rendering text to an image and so all of
these nodes these create images and so I
like to categorize these as image nodes
and I'm going to do a fancy pants thing
here I'm going to select all of these
nodes go up to effects under Tools under
flow there's a tool called underlay if I
double click on that that's going to
make a little background behind my nodes
it's like a little tray that these
things sit in and if I double click off
and I can grab this little tray and move
it around and it's going to move those
all at once which is really convenient
especially when you have a bunch of
nodes now I can rename any node by
selecting it and hitting F2 on the
keyboard okay if I want to deselect any
nodes I can double click and that's
going to deselect everything and if I
alt click on this underlay I can select
just the underlay by itself so not all
the nodes just the underlay and I can
hit F2
to rename that and so we're going to
rename this
image nodes I can even right click and
say set color let's just make those
green okay image nodes all those do is
either open an image or create an image
and they output an image the next type
of node would be an effect node and
there are lots and lots of different
effect nodes so some examples would be
like our
blur and if we grab this node look at it
the blur itself if I hit one on the
keyboard there isn't any image there
because an effect needs an image in
order to exist so if I were to take this
text and plug this into the yellow input
of the blur now we have something
showing up on this left viewer if I push
up the blur size we're going to have
blurry text and so an effect node
adjusts an image that goes into it I can
grab this and hold shift and I can drag
this down down in between a couple of
nodes like that to link it up I'll close
my effects here so we have a little more
room and here we have a blurry image on
both
viewers the reason for that is because
we're looking at the blur on the left
viewer and the media out on the right
viewer and we're always viewing the
output of each
node if I were to take this media in one
and drag this to the left we can see
kind of the before and the after let's
do a couple other effects great effect
would be our color corrector and I want
you to notice something here we're
putting this image into the input and
then we're taking the output of the
effect and putting that into the media
out so we're running an image through
the effect we're not putting an effect
on top of it or applying it or anything
like that it's easier to wrap your head
around this if you always think I'm
going to run an image through an effect
I'm going to run this through a blur I'm
going to run this through a color
corrector then I can adjust this color
corrector and look now we have this kind
of purpley image because we've taken our
original image we've color corrected it
and now it's in the media out and then
of course if we go to the edit page we
have this purpley image right so we
always run images through
effects there's a bunch of different
effects like curves or brightness and
contrast and they all work in a similar
ways you always run an image through
them and then you can adjust that image
in the inspector and kind of control how
strong that effect is same thing for
brightness and
contrast same thing here I can adjust
the contrast of the image just by
running it through that brightness and
contrast node cool right I can hold
shift and just move this a little bit to
disconnect it and I can hold shift and
drop whatever I want to actually be
connected there back on the line and
it's always a good idea if you're going
to connect something like that using
shift or dragging something down from
the toolbar that you take it and kind of
shake it around and make sure that it's
actually connected because you can
really easily have this node sitting on
that line and it looks like it's
connected but it's not and so if you're
going to drop it on the line like that
always just kind of check and make sure
that it's connected so these nodes right
here these are effect nodes now instead
of going up to my effects panel every
time I want to add something that's not
on the toolbar here I'm going to use a
little shortcut I can hit shift and hit
space bar and that's going to bring up
my select tool panel and I can type any
node that I want I'm going to typee un d
That's shorthand for underlay and then
hit add and that's going to add my
underlay okay same thing I'm going to
resize
this double click off of it and hold alt
and click here and hit F2 to rename it
we'll call this effect nodes and we'll
make this a color let's just make it
teal yeah that's nice so far we have
image nodes and effect
nodes and if this is making sense so far
that's really great but here's the thing
when we were talking about compositing
we were talking about combining
different images together which I feel
like a lot of people are used to doing
with layers so if you have some kind of
layer-based compositing program or photo
editing program or even here on the edit
page we can take multiple different
layers and put them on top of each other
right but in Fusion you might hunt
around and quickly find that that there
is no layers panel there's no way to
stack things like that there's no way to
put an image over another image in any
of these panels so what the heck do we
do just take this blur off here for a
minute how are we supposed to put fog
over this shot or you know put a moon in
the background or whatever we're going
to do if we can't actually combine
images together well that's where our
next type of node comes in and that is a
merge
node so to the right of the second
little divider here this first little
icon is merge so I can take this merge
node and drag this here and you'll
notice this merge node not only has a
yellow input and a gray output but it
also has a green input and a blue input
now this is something we haven't really
talked about yet the main image input
for most nodes is generally this yellow
input okay for an effect node it's just
called input if you Mouse over any of
these it'll sort of tell you what these
are but each input has a different name
and a different job here on the color
corrector node we can put another image
into this which is called a match
reference we also have a match mask this
blue input is an effect mask input which
we'll get into in a minute but the merge
node has a yellow input which is called
the background and the green input which
is called the foreground that's because
every node has one specific job and the
Mer's job is to put one image over
another image so if we were to take our
media in and plug this into the yellow
input of the merge and take the merge
into media out here in the right viewer
we see nothing different happening
that's because if you were to read this
flowchart we have media in which is take
this image from the timeline and then go
into the merge the merge has one job put
the foreground over the background there
is no foreground so we're just going to
see the background and then we put that
into media out one and so now we have
the background but if we want to put
something over it like a layer on top of
it like let's say we want to put some
text over it we can grab a text node
which again is an image
node and we'll call
this text FG for
foreground and I'll take the output of
this text and plug that into the green
input of our merge and look what happens
now we have the text over our background
so that's how you would combine two
images in Fusion now don't get hung up
on this because it can be confusing when
you have to use a merge node and when
you don't if you're used to thinking
about you know dropping a color
corrector on something like even in the
edit page right if we have an effect we
go to
effects grab one of our open effects
here and we'll take this blur we
physically take this blur and drag it on
top of our footage and that's how we add
that
blur so we're dropping it on top right
but that's why I was saying we should
always think about running something
through an effect because you're never
going to put an effect on top of
something in Fusion it just doesn't work
that way you always run an image through
an effect and so this merge all it does
is put an image over another image if we
were to do something like grab a
blur and plug that into our merge one
like this I see a lot of newbies 2
Fusion doing this you put that blur over
that merge
and then you select the blur and you
just pump that blur size and nothing's
happening nothing's nothing's changing
that's
because what you're trying to do is blur
this image but instead what you're
telling it to do is take this image and
blur nothing and put that blurred
nothing over this image which just looks
like the regular image right but if we
were to take an image and run it through
an effect before we merge it then we
have our blurry foreground our text on
top of our background and we can think
about this in order right so we take our
text and then we blur it and then we put
it over our
background and of course that's what we
get we have blurry text over our
background because what we're really
doing if I just drag this blur to the
left is we're creating an image with
this effect we're taking an image
running it through an effect and it
makes a new image with the effect
applied then we can take that image and
put this over our existing
image so a merge always puts a
foreground image over a background image
okay that's the only time you use a
merge it's when you're putting something
over something else and you never put
effects on top of things you only run
images through effects okay if you wrap
your head around that everything's going
to be so much easier believe me you
might be asking how do I stack multiple
things if a merge only puts a foreground
over a background what if I have three
layers let's just grab another text here
and we'll just call this layer three and
we'll make it a different color make it
kind of this blue if I take this text
and I plug that into this other input of
our
merge uh some weird stuff is happening
no nobody really even knows what's going
on
here and it looks like we're just going
to keep putting images into this merge
in stack them but what we're really
doing is hooking this text up to our
mask input which again we're going to go
over in a minute but that's just not
what we want to do if we want to put
another image over these two images all
we do is we make another merge so I can
take this merge and put this here in the
flow and then take the output of our
text and put that there and so now we
have layer one which is the background
of the merge Layer Two which is the
foreground of this merge those get
merged together and put into the
background of this merge and then layer
three goes into the foreground and so
that's generally how you would layer
things here in fusion and really the
best way to think about this is your
layers kind of Stack from left to right
so this first layer is media in and then
this is our second layer this is our
third layer and so on you kind of build
them from left to
right if you want to change the order of
the layers you can select the merge and
the image that you plugged into the
merge you can hold shift and you can
drag this out of the flow like that and
just drop it in before this merge and
now we have the blurry text over this
blue layer and so the order of the nodes
matters generally goes from left to
right now something to mention it
doesn't have to go from left to right
that's just kind of its default in fact
when you move these nodes around you'll
see that these inputs actually kind of
move around with them you could stack
this from top to bottom or right to left
if you wanted to or bottom to top it
doesn't really matter what matters is
what nodes you have connected to what
inputs so like the colors of the inputs
that's what's important now something to
mention there is a node called a multi
merge node and this is relatively new in
the later versions of resolve and if
you're coming from a layer-based app
this might be more helpful for you but
I'm going to give this to you with a
caveat this works pretty much exact like
a normal merge node I can drag this here
in the
flow just disconnect this stuff and
we'll plug the blur two into multi-
merge and that's going to do what a
normal merge node does but once we have
this plugged in we'll see we have
another white input and this says Layer
Two so if we take this text three and
plug this into the white input well now
we have kind of what we were looking to
do earlier is we have our first layer
our background then we have layer one
then we have the next layer and then we
have the next layer in fact if we select
this multi merge we can see a list of
our layers and we can select each layer
and we can adjust properties of the
layer and we can drag the order around
in the layers right so if you're really
into layers this is a good way to use
layers within fusion and you can connect
as many layers as you want to this multi
merge
here's the caveat here's the warning
that I would give you about that let's
say we
have a whole bunch of text nodes and we
connect these all to a multi merge you
can see where things start to get a
little bit crazy because they're kind of
spider webbing out of this multi merge
and I mean you could totally put these
in a stack like this to kind of hint to
yourself what is the top layer and
what's the bottom layer and that might
be a good way to do it but check this
out
if you move the layers around in the
layer list like this this isn't accurate
anymore and so you have to manage two
different things in order to keep
yourself organized and this is kind of a
problem because one of the major
benefits of nodes is being able to look
at a node chart and understand exactly
what's happening without having to
select something and go into a layer
list and look at all of the Hidden
properties that might be there right so
we could have this size pushed up in the
center changed or whatever on one of
these
layers and without it selected I have no
idea which layer this is I have no idea
why it's moved around I have no
indication of that and so I'm going to
have to go through any of these and see
if there's any sizing or anything weird
and no that's not working so I can go
into the multi merge and I'll have to
look at each of these to see if there's
any SI there it is there's the sizing
and so you're just searching for things
over and over again
and it's honestly just a worse way to
work you're kind of making things hard
for yourself and so as uncomfortable as
it might be I would really recommend not
using the multi merch I would recommend
if you want to Stack a bunch of layers
that you get used to making a bunch of
merge nodes like this and building your
layer stack essentially from left to
right like
this because then you can see the images
that are connected and the exact order
in which they're connected and it's all
laid out here on the nodes and you can
tell from a
glance and if you are going to move
things around like this I would also
recommend using something like a
transform node so here right under our
playback controls there's this little
icon this is a transform node and this
is an
effect okay you run an image through it
and then it just gives you some
properties for sizing and angle and
flipping things and centering it mov mov
it around and that kind of thing and
again it's for that reason just at a
glance I can tell what's happening with
all of my layers I have three different
layers and it's really easy for me to
tell which one is probably moved around
and changed it's the one with the
transform node on it right it's this one
right here and I don't have to go and
hunt and search and everything which one
is blurry probably the one with the blur
note on it now what you might be
thinking is dang that seems like a lot
of work for something really simple I
think I'll just stick with layers is
because man then I don't have to make a
merge node and you know add all of these
nodes just to do one basic thing right
but here's the thing it's really about
the same amount of work as adding a
layer check this out you have to make
the image right you have to generate the
text or bring in the file or anything
like that and so no matter what app you
use you're going to have to do that I'll
just get rid of this merge node for a
minute and bring our media in over here
and if you want to put this on top of
this other image it's actually about the
same amount of work because what you can
do is you can take this output and drag
the output over the output of this node
and look what happens boom it makes a
merge node and it automatically connects
this to the foreground and so you don't
have to make a merge node and connect it
and disconnect things and all that stuff
every time you can make a node connect
it pretty quickly right and once you get
used to doing things this way then I
mean it goes pretty quick it's really
not that big of a deal
and then you have this flowchart that
you can read easily and see everything
that's happening to your image all along
the pipeline and so that's really how A
merge
Works let's take this merge node and
we'll put an underlay
here okay we'll have a merge and a multi
merge so that's the third type of node a
merge node so we have images effects and
merges the last major kind of node would
be a mask
now to the right of this middle divider
here we have these little shapes I'll
just grab the ellipse to start out with
and what this does if we hit one on the
keyboard is it creates a circle and it
does this with a little shape that you
can
adjust and in the inspector you can
soften the shape and all of that kind of
stuff and this is designed to select
part of the screen and if you connect
this to a mass input in any node you're
essentially telling whatever that node's
job is to only happen inside of the Mask
so let's say we were going to run this
image through a color corrector and make
it purple here what we could
do is connect our mask to the blue input
of this color character and look what
happens it's only going to do that color
correction inside of this mask and so
you can limit where the node does its
job by telling it to do it inside of the
Mask you could also select the mask and
go over here and hit invert and have it
only do it outside of the mask and there
are a few different kinds of masks
there's the ellipse mask there is a
rectangle
mask which works in a similar way it
just makes a rectangle
instead we also have a polygon mask
which lets you draw on the screen kind
of like the pen
tool you can make your own
shape and we also have a beast bline
which is sort of similar to the polygon
but it kind of rounds out the shape so
you can't have harsh Corners you can
only have these kind of soft Corners
like this and so this is great for more
organic shapes and if you want kind of
softer rounder shapes but regardless of
how you draw the shape these all work
the same way they're designed to be
connected to the blue input of any node
that you want to limit let's bring this
over
here make an
underlay these are mask nodes and so I
know Fusion might seem really
overwhelming with all of these nodes but
really again there's there's only four
different kinds of nodes that you really
need to know there's image nodes there's
effect nodes merges and masks and these
are the big categories
and so we can use these categories and
combine these together in different ways
to adjust our images and make movie
Magic make visual effects make
animations make Motion Graphics all of
this stuff is really cool and we use
nodes to do it so now that we have a
good idea of how nodes work in Fusion
let's actually make something right just
kind of make this a little bigger so
that we can
see and we're going to make this a
nighttime shot
and add some
fog the first thing I'm going to do is a
little bit of color management and this
is kind of just as basic as it gets when
it comes to compositing in the upper
right hand corner here there's this
little lattice and where it says let
here I can go down and I can pick a lot
to view this footage with and this is
shot on
Blackmagic pocket 6K and gen5 so let's
just say Blackmagic Gen 5 filmed a video
and that's going to give us a decent
approxim of what this will look like
when we use some color grading on it so
this is obviously too bright and
everything so let's do something like
take a color corrector and we'll just
drag this in here and this is stuff we
can do a little bit on the color page
but let's at least just take some of
this down a little bit to make this a
little bit more of a nighttime shot and
I'll also cool this off take down some
of the
saturation and we'll just do a little
bit
more kind of Darkness
here something like that that's looking
more night timey and then let's just
look at this and say okay what what
needs some work well this sky is pretty
bright so again this might be stuff that
we can do in the color page but just to
practice a little bit of fusion here we
can take something like the color
curves and I'm just going to look at the
sky and I'll uncheck Alpha here and just
take this down a little bit bit
something like
that maybe even push a little bit of
blue into
this take out some of the
red take out some of the green just to
give us this kind of bluish sky and then
we're going to mask this color with a
mask so let's just connect this polygon
here and I'm just going to kind of draw
in our shape
here like this
and we're just isolating this to the Sky
boom like
that push up the soft Edge a little bit
and that looks a lot better so now we
have this kind of set up as a night
scene now let's add the brightness of
these lights back in now check this out
here's something we could do let's also
just take another color corrector and
this time I'm going to take this media
in this is our original footage and I
can actually drag multiple outputs from
the same node so I can put this into our
color corrector like this and if I hit
one on the keyboard I can bring up and
see what we're doing I'll also make sure
that we're looking at this under our l
so black magic design gen film like that
maybe make this just a little bit
warmer and I'll take the gain down a
little bit but we're looking for kind of
a nice yellow tone here because we want
to accentuate what these lights look
like okay great and now we can take this
brighter col color and I'll take the
output of this and merge it over
everything else this and now we have
this as kind of a second layer on top of
everything but we can isolate this with
a
polygon and we'll just draw a little
shape around here like
that feather that out and you see what
we're doing here see that let's do the
same thing over here I'm just going to
grab another polygon and just plug it
right into this polygon mask that's
going to stack these
masks like this and I'll just soft Edge
like that can make this a little bit
bigger whatever we
think maybe even make this a lot bigger
and soften it a
lot so we have a little bit of light
coming in
here let's also do that for this light
here I'll stack
this like
this again soft soft soft
soft and now we have this somewhat
convincing night shot with those Bright
Lights there kind of contrasting with
the blue and we can further refine this
in the color page but you know that's
kind of a basic nice
composite let's go ahead and rename
things this color corrector we're just
going to call this light
CC this will be Sky
curves this will be night
CC this polygon let's call Sky
mask and these polygons will'll say you
know light mask
mid light mask left and light mask right
so now we can see exactly what's
happening here let's just take this
media and we'll say OG for original
footage Mi like that and we can see that
we're color correcting this we are color
correcting the sky just inside of the
sky mask and then we're merging the
original footage over itself with some
masks here we have it color corrected
and that's what gives us this nighttime
look now let's add a little bit of fog
this is something you definitely can't
do in the color page we can grab this
fast noise here I'll take this and then
drag this in like that that's going to
make this big bright kind of cloud if we
push up the detail a little bit push
down the scale we can see these clouds
like this
one thing we'll do is take this merge
and turn the blend all the way down and
then we'll just start to push it up a
little bit just to where we can start to
see that a little
bit and then we're going to mask this
also so we'll just take this
polygon and we'll mask this just along
the
ground mostly over here on the left
where it's kind of farther away from
camera we'll soften that a little bit
and we'll have this fog just end up
right here inside of this mask and one
thing I'm I'm going to do with this fog
is under merge here I'm just going to
take this subtractive additive all the
way down to subtractive and that's just
going to make this blend in just a
little bit
nicer and take the detail down just a
little kind of adjust
this so we have a little bit more
realistic looking fog here also take the
blend down just a
touch the other thing I'll do with this
fast noise is push up the SE rate a
little bit and that's going to kind of
animate this over time
maybe not quite that much just want a
little bit take the contrast down a
touch just
want little bit of fog here and we're
also going to animate the
center now we haven't talked a lot about
animation here but what we can do is any
of these properties we can animate over
time by clicking this
diamond and changing its value so here
at zero let's go ahead and click the
diamond here here on Center and then
towards the end of the shot we're going
to go towards the end and then this time
I don't need to click the diamond I can
just change this property and it's going
to animate it in between these
two
values so now we have
this fog kind of rolling through like
that you know and depending on how
realistic you want this to be you can
spend a little bit more time on it but
that's kind of the workflow here but
let's kind of break this down I'll hit
one one on the keyboard to bring up the
different parts here so we starting with
our original footage then we're doing
some color correction we're color
correcting the sky we're doing a little
bit of color correction on the original
footage and then merging it over itself
just where those lights
are so that gives us this nice kind of
nighttime looking
shot then we're taking this fast noise
we're putting it over the shot only
inside of the mask and now we have some
fog and we're animating the fog over
time to kind of roll through the
shot pretty cool stuff you can do in
Fusion let's take a look at the next
shot in our timeline I'm just going to
disable this top layer for a minute we
have some footage of a little spaceship
and then we have some footage that we
shot Weeks Later of our little alien
puppet and a common thing that you might
want to do is take a piece of footage
and kind of put it inside of something
and so we want to put this little
guy into the cockpit of our spaceship
this is a perfect thing to do in Fusion
so to get both of
these clips into Fusion at the same time
we can simply just right click here with
them both selected and go up to new
Fusion clip that's going to combine
those together and then when we go to
Fusion it's going to have these clips
already put into a merge node so let's
arrange these I like to put the
background coming in on the left and the
foreground coming in on the top that
just helps me again it doesn't really
matter because you could have the
foreground coming in on the left it's
the foreground because it's connected to
the green input right but just so that I
don't get lost I like to put the
background on the left foreground on the
right let's take a look at what the
background is this is going to be our
spaceship uncore Mi this is our alien Mi
and so now how do we put this little guy
in in there well I'm actually going to
switch these because I want my alien to
be in the background and my spaceship to
be in the foreground cuz what we're
going to do is just cut a hole out of
this footage and we're going to see the
alien through it so to quickly switch a
background and a foreground on a merge
you can select the merge and hit control
t on the keyboard or command t on a Mac
so now you'll see these colors are
switching so be careful cuz you might
accidentally hit that and guess what
things are switched so now we have the
alien in the background and the
spaceship in the foreground let's go
ahead and just bring our spaceship up
here in this first viewer and I'm going
to add a mask
now let's do this with our polygon I'll
grab the polygon and connect it to the
spaceship anytime that you're going to
mask something directly like cut
something out of a picture it's a good
idea to bring that picture up in the
first viewer and draw directly on it
rather than drawing down the line
there's a lot of reasons for that but
it'll save you some major headaches if
you do it this way but I can't see what
I'm drawing on so I'm going to select
this polygon and go over here to this
little switch and I'm going to turn off
the switch and that's going to show my
background it won't apply the polygon
but I can still draw it so I'm going to
hold control and zoom in here and I'm
just going to start here in this corner
and just make a nice cutout of
our cockpit
here just clicking and dragging
and just kind of cutting out where I
think we could look back and see the
alien something like this boom now if we
don't have a perfect corner right here I
can grab the little handles here I can
hold control and I can move one handle
at a time so that's really helpful for
something like this with a sharp corner
like that and now if I go over here to
my polygon and apply the
mask it's going to only draw this
spaceship media in inside of the Mask
which is not quite what we want let's go
over here to the mask select
that and then here in the inspector
where it says invert let's click invert
and that's going to just kind of cut out
a little window here now we have our
alien showing through in the back that's
great but he's the wrong size so if we
want to resize him we can use a
transform node which is right here under
the stop button grab this and drag this
in let's take this transform and we'll
scale him and look we're kind of scaling
him in this little
window and we just got to position him
where he feels good let's rotate him a
little
bit that's pretty good maybe we'll make
him just a touch bigger like he's kind
of stuffed in there there's our little
man and now because we have similar
lighting and everything this is going to
work pretty well cuz we planned this
shot right the only other thing that I
might do is this mask just seems a
little bit harsh and so let's just take
this polygon
mask we'll zoom in here and we'll just
take this soft edge Up Just a Touch just
so it looks realistic it matches with
the other edges and everything that's
going to do just
fine now I mean you almost can't even
tell that we did that which is the goal
that's the point of visual effects right
so there's our little
guy that works pretty well one thing
we'll do just to make this a little bit
more believable is we should add a
little Shadow to him right here we can
do that a bunch of different ways but I
think what we'll do is after this
transform let's add a little color
correction and we'll darken this down
we'll just take the gain down a little
bit like that maybe the gamma down a
touch and we're going to use a mask and
we're going to limit this color
character with a mask we'll just add
kind of a soft mask
here like that and then give that a
really soft Edge
now he has a little subtle Shadow on his
forehead here we could even make that a
little bit more pronounced just so we
can see it just take the gamma down a
touch now here's before and here's after
we're just adding a little bit of
Darkness
there I feel like that helps sell it a
little bit yeah
great and so there's our comp we have
our little guy peeking out of the
spaceship and this is already in the
edit timeline so if I go over to edit
boom there we are there's our comp with
our guy he's looking out oh man he's so
handsome Fusion is perfect for things
like this where you just need to adjust
your shot do some visual effects by the
way this video is coming up looking kind
of weird because we don't have that L on
it that we did here in Fusion but when
we do our color
correction this is going to end up
looking pretty good so we're kind of
just keeping this in a ungraded mode
this shot we already kind of preg graded
just for this training so it's just a
little less things to deal with it's
working for this last shot let's say we
want this to be some kind of motion
title we could go over to Fusion like
this and start adding text and animating
it and everything like that
here but the problem is that when we go
to color grade this we're also going to
be color grading our graphics and so a
smart hard thing to do would be to back
up a little bit I'm just going to right
click and reset our Fusion composition
so it doesn't have to think through
Fusion every single time hit reset
that'll just bring that back to normal
footage and let's go over to effects and
under effects there's a couple effects
here one is an adjustment clip the other
is a fusion composition what we can do
when we're making Graphics is we can
make a fusion composition either in the
media pool by right clicking and saying
new Fusion composition
or just from our effects panel we can
just drag a fusion composition in here
just like we would a
title and what this is going to do is be
kind of our Standalone title so now if I
hit
Fusion we can start with a background
just take this background like this and
take some text and put that on
top the name of this film is called
Tuesday on
Earth and let's just make sure this is
working here let's head back to our edit
page and yes we see Tuesday on Earth but
we don't see the footage under it that's
because this background is solid black
so what we can do is just take this
Alpha down like this and now we'll see
our footage under it a little trick if
you are going to make something like
this you can either do it with a fusion
composition like that or you could even
make an adjustment
clip you can take this adjustment
clip and put this sort of in the same
place and then go into fusion and you'll
see the background behind it so our
media in is just what you see in the
timeline but if we make this
text we still have this
separated as a separate layer and if we
were to move this over like this that's
just going to be over whatever our
background is when we get into the color
page we can choose not to put color on
our adjustment clip so this might be a
better way to actually do it right now
is using an adjustment clip and just
switching over to Fusion so that we can
see kind of how this looks over our
footage and let's go ahead and just
change the
font I like this font called Poppins you
can get this on like Google fonts and
everything it's
free I'll just push up the size and
maybe push up the tracking a little bit
I like something like that that looks
nice and from here I mean man we can
just do anything so let's do something
crazy let's use this text as a mask and
we'll take this footage and we'll mask
the footage over itself with the text
this is crazy sauce so I'm just going to
disconnect the text here and let's take
a transform node and plug this media in
into the transform node then we can
merge that over and it looks like
nothing's happened but let's go ahead
and flip this upside down like this and
we can move this around with our
transform node and we can see that we
have a layer over itself like this
so maybe let's do this and then let's
take this text and let's just use this
text as a mask for our merge we could do
it for the
transform which um might actually give
us the same
result because we're only going to
transform this inside of where the text
is but if we want to add other things
like color correction and stuff like
this it would be more problematic and so
if I hold shift and take this text out I
can put this text into the mask input of
the merge and we get the same idea but a
little bit more flexibility
later let's just maybe do this and then
maybe we'll add some color
correction to our
transform and maybe let's desaturate it
push the gamma down or something like
that so now we have this really cool
looking
title which we can animate and do all
kinds of stuff like let's take this
transform and we can animate this angle
let's take the angle here and we'll just
maybe move that a little
bit and then by the end we'll have this
moving like
that so now we have this really crazy
looking title it's really unique I mean
you aren't going to see this in a
template or anything like that that's
pretty
cool it's just unique to this film
pretty cool we could also animate the
text so let's just animate the tracking
maybe so I'll go to the beginning
beginning of our shot go over here to
tracking and let's click the key frame
diamond and then at the end of our shot
we'll just push the tracking together
ever so slightly so now we have this
really slow kind of
movement on our title oh so
cool so
cool and this is just scratching the
surface of the things that we can do in
Fusion you can do absolutely anything
it's a fully featured compositing app
you can do visual effects you can do
Graphics you can do I mean all kinds of
stuff we even made a broadcast quality
cartoon just using the tools in fusion
and that was a whole lot of fun you just
have like absolute freedom that's why I
like Fusion so much so cool but I think
that we've dove in here enough to give
you a good idea of what Fusion can do
give you some practice shots here make
sure to download these work files and
open this up and see if you can cut out
this little window and put your little
guy there turn this shot into a night
shot just using nodes what you've
learned so far and maybe even make some
cool graphics like this so neat if all
this Fusion stuff seems really exciting
and you want to dive deeper make sure to
check out our D Vinci resolve resources
guide which is available right there
where we've gathered some of the best
resources for learning Fusion this is
courses tools templates all the things
that you would need that's available
right now and you can get it for free if
you click on the card right there let's
keep going all right now we're going to
talk about the color page in the work
files if you open up a timeline if you
go to the bin five color page double
click on color page start that's where
I'm going to be starting
from you can just open that up in the
edit page if you want to and then switch
over to color you can also just double
click it here in the media pool in the
color page which again works the same as
the media pool in the other pages so
this page is also a little bit
intimidating although maybe not so much
as the fusion page but there are quite a
bit of controls and panels and things
that are hidden and all these little
buttons to play around with and it can
sort of feel like you're sitting at the
Helm of the Space Shuttle or something
but here's the good news you don't need
to know all of this stuff you really
only need to know a couple of things in
order to be dangerous with color and
adjust your footage and color grade your
movies and make them look beamus so why
use the color page well let's kind of
talk about the ways that
maybe you've experienced doing some
color correction if you haven't used
Vinci resolve generally how it works in
whatever nle you're working with is you
have some kind of color corrector effect
and you drag that onto whatever shot you
want to do some color grading on then
you double click on that shot and open
it up in some kind of properties panel
and do your adjustments right and that's
how you can adjust your shots and make
them match together make them look the
way that you want the problem with that
is that it's super inefficient because
you have to put it on every shot double
click on it adjust it go to the next
shot you might be able to copy and paste
the effects to different shots or you
might have something like an adjustment
layer that you put that on top and you
can have some common effects on multiple
shots but then you have to go in and add
the same color corrector to your other
shots and it's just kind of a big
pain the way the color page works is
whatever shot you're looking at in your
viewer that's the shot that you're going
to be adjusting and so you just have to
play through your movie and wherever
your playhead is there are controls down
below and when you touch the controls it
adjusts the shot that you're looking at
and that's how it works and so you don't
have to add different effects or you
know go through all this crazy stuff you
just look at what you want to adjust and
adjust it so it's really really simple
and that's kind of the first thing I
would say is that even though this looks
more complicated than you know using a
three-way color corrector using metry or
something that you might be familiar
with it's really just as simple as
looking at the footage that you want to
adjust and grabbing controls and that
adjusts that image so let's talk a
little bit about the big ideas of color
correction before we even dive into the
color page really when we're talking
about color uh one of the big things
that we need to do is take our footage
from a log image if you're shooting in
log that's kind of this gray desaturated
image and make it look decent on the
screen so this would be a corrected
image this is something that you might
see people do by just pushing up the
contrast and the saturation and that is
effectively what's happening but really
the best thing to do here is use color
management we'll get into that in a
second and so that would be kind of the
first step is use some color management
and then when we talk about color
correction uh we really want the image
to look realistic look like there's
nothing really distracting happening so
if it's underexposed it's too dark or
too bright we can adjust that exposure
if there's not enough contrast we can
add more contrast if the colors aren't
quite bright enough we can adjust the
saturation if the whole thing looks way
too yellow we can take some of that
yellow out and this is kind of the goal
at the end is to have an image that
looks correct looks uh kind of like it
looked when we shot it like what we
intended it to look like on top of that
we can add some creative looks to our
footage so we can take this nice looking
image and add some style to it you know
and build some kind of different
feelings one that might look a little
bit more harsh one that might look a
little bit Kinder and then one that's
you know black and white there's all
these different kind of possibilities
and ways to change the mood just by
playing with the colors on this exact
same shot another major thing that we'll
be doing during the color grading color
correction phase is matching shots these
two shots look like they belong together
this shot is a little bit too blue and
too bright and so these don't really
match but these two do so it's a matter
of making sure that all of the shots
feel like they live in the same world
and that there isn't some distracting
difference between the wide shot and the
closeup this I think is probably one of
the harder parts of doing color grading
because you can make one image look good
but to have an entire scene look good
together takes a little bit more work
and finessing another thing that we'll
do in the color page is talk about
secondary Corrections so these are
Corrections that we would do to just
parts of the image or certain colors so
it's not about the image as a whole and
how it matches and that kind of thing
but it's finessing things a little bit
like you know darkening one side of the
frame or making the window a little bit
more blue or adjusting a specific color
like oh this shirt should look a little
bit more maroon and less red that's
where we get a little bit more detailed
this is the stuff that's really fun but
it's kind of a lot less important than
the basics than the primary color
grading skills so that's all stuff that
we can do in the color page let's take a
look at the interface here of course we
have our media pool on the left in the
middle we have our viewer and this is
going to be whatever shot we're working
on basically wherever our playhead is in
the timeline and to the right we have
our color nodes now after going into
Fusion these are just going to be so
easy since we already talked about what
nodes are these are like a much simpler
version of nodes but it kind of works
the same way instead of a media in and a
media out we have this green input and
the green output and it flows from left
to right through these nodes every shot
has one node to start out with you can
add another node by right clicking and
saying add node and there are several
different kinds of nodes the one you
mostly use would be a Serial node so add
serial like this and unlike the fusion
page this node can have a lot of
different jobs it's not just one job
what we really do is we use these to
kind of group together different ideas
for color correction so this first one
might be to fix the exposure the second
one might be to fix the saturation we
might have a third one that adds some
contrast and we kind of split these up
up so that we can turn one off or on at
any point and kind of test things out
and make sure that that specific thing
that we're doing is making the image
better so more on nodes in a little bit
once we actually get color grading kind
of in the middle of our interface we
have our clips and this is pretty simple
you just click on the shot that you want
to adjust and it's going to jump to that
shot kind of similar below it is we have
our mini timeline a lot of the time I
just close this it's good for reference
to see kind of where you're at in your
edit timeline but it does take up space
and most of the time I just want to
click through the different shots and so
a lot of the time I'll just go up here
to where it says timeline and click that
to close it again the color page opens
the timeline from whatever sequence you
have open so if we go to edit page it's
this sequence right here and all of the
color correction lives in the timeline
and so if I go over here to color and I
push one of these wheels and make it
purpley Pink and go back to the edit
page there it is purple pink kind of in
a similar way to how Fusion does
things okay I'll just reset that by
clicking this little reset all
button and down below our timelines we
have this section of our screen and if
yours looks different than mine like
it's not split up into three different
pallets it's maybe split into two or
even one don't worry about it that is
based on your
resolution and your UI scaling and stuff
in your OS and so if you don't quite
like your layout there might be a way to
you know change the resolution of your
monitor or change your display scaling
and get this to layout a little bit
differently but that's what it's based
on either way no matter what the layout
is you're going to have all of the same
panels that I have the free version of
resolve isn't going to have the emotion
effects panel or the 3D panel right here
but everything else should be there and
be the same and there are a lot of
buttons here kind of at the top and what
those do is switch out these different
pallets to different tools and there are
quite a few of them in fact some of
these tools even have sub tools like
this and there's different versions of
it so I mean it's just it gets really
deep again you don't need to know all of
these we're going to walk through the
ones that are the most useful and most
helpful and then you know on your own
time if you want to dive in and start
getting a little bit deeper in some of
the other palettes then you can do that
I'm going to go ahead and close our
media pool so that we can see our
footage here and let's just go to shot
10 right here and we're going to start
out talking about the primaries color
wheels that's this lower left pette that
has these rainbow circles and even
though it looks like there's just a lot
going on here there's really only three
different kinds of controls and we'll
just start out by playing with the
offset go ahead and grab this middle Dot
and move this around and what that's
going to do is change the overall color
of our
footage so the farther we push it away
from the Middle the stronger that color
is going to be and then the direction in
which we push it is going to determine
the actual Hue the color that we're
pushing into the image you can reset
this using that little reset button and
down below it below these numbers we
have this little slider you can grab
this and move this to the right or to
the left and when you move it to the
right it brightens the image when you
bring it to the left it darkens the
image and so already we have quite a bit
of tools to be able to adjust our image
just with these two controls so if I
wanted to make this warm and dark I can
push it towards warm and take this
slider down here this is called the
master wheel take this master wheel and
push it to the left and that's going to
darken down my
footage again I can reset that by
clicking the reset button here and now
we're back to where we were anytime I'm
make any change to the colors of an
image the clip gets this little Rainbow
highlight so you can tell the clips that
you've adjusted versus the ones that you
haven't so the only thing we've touched
is shot 10 so far now why are there the
other Wheels here well these are the
exact same kind of controls but they're
designed to adjust certain ranges of
brightness in the image and from left to
right it's the darkest parts of the
image kind of the middle brightness and
the brightest parts of the image and
they're called lift gamma and gain lift
is the darkest parts and so if I were to
push the lift into blue we'll see the
darkest parts of our image kind of Turn
Blue the gamma is the middle and so if I
push that that's going to be just the
middle parts of the image and then the
gain is going to be stronger in the
brightest parts of the image so we see
this kind of back here in the window a
little bit more and this is how we can
take some major control over our image
right let's say we want to have a little
a little bit more contrast here we could
take the brightest parts and push those
up with the master wheel and the darkest
parts and push them down with that
Master wheel and we get a little bit
more contrast we can take the middle the
gamma and push that around to give us
kind of some different looks and we have
tons of control in this image just from
learning how the Color Wheel Works and
the master wheel cuz we can already do
everything all at once or do a little
bit stronger correction in the brighter
Parts the midtones or the darkest parts
so now that we have this pushed up a
little bit maybe I want the brighter
parts to be a little warm maybe I want
the darker parts to be a little
cool now we're adding a little bit of
style to our footage that wasn't there
before I'll go ahead and hit this reset
all button to get rid of everything that
we've done in this one little panel and
the other major control that you need to
know are the primary controls they're
the little numbers that go across the
top and across the bottom of this panel
and you can grab this number and push it
to the right or left and I can push this
to the right and add more contrast for
contrast or less contrast pivot is based
on contrast so it's kind of decides what
it thinks is bright versus dark and the
contrast is how different they are so
you can kind of play around and get some
unique looks with that just reset
everything again midtone detail adds a
little bit of diffusion to the midtones
it kind of decreases the contrast and
then it increases the contrast if you
push it to the right and so you can make
somebody look a lot more rough a little
bit older uglier by pushing up the
midtone detail or kind of younger and
softer by pushing it to the left we have
the temperature and tint which is a
great way to fix white balance we have
our saturation which is sort of here
under gain that's just the brightness of
the colors the Hue is the
actual Hues of the colors themselves
and there are a few other controls that
we might talk about later but you can
play around with them see what they do
so now just knowing what we know only
learning three different controls here
in the color page we can really do a lot
we can do a lot with this image so let's
say that we want this to look good we
could push up the gain push down the
lift and push up the saturation maybe
push down the gamma a little bit and we
have what looks like a pretty normal
image and that's a a lot better than our
log image which if I want to turn off
all of my color correction I can click
this little rainbow sparkle
button and we can look at the difference
that we made so that's obviously a big
difference right this second image is
much better and so we have a lot of
control over adjusting our image just in
this primaries palette if you're not
super super into color I would honestly
probably just stop there cuz you can do
so much stuff with the primary color
wheels and one node that you can
probably make your movie look nice
especially if you shot it decently you
can probably make it look nice just with
the primary color wheels pretty cool but
I'm going to reset this because that way
of fixing this log image isn't really
the very best way to do it it works and
that's actually how some people do it
and they can make nice looking things
but what we're doing when we just kind
of willy-nilly start pushing the colors
around and putting some contrast into
this and adding some saturation and
everything is we're deciding a bunch of
stuff ourselves we're kind of getting
creative with this image which is fine
except for we don't really need to what
we're really looking to do is make this
look not log and so the quicker and
better way to do that one job is with
something called color management color
management is just a scientific way to
go from log footage into footage that
looks good on your screen instead of
kind of washed out in Gray and there are
a few different ways to do color
management one of the ways is if you go
down to the lower right hand corner of
our screen you can click on the settings
Cog and that's going to bring up our
project settings if we go over here to
this third item down we can go to color
management and this is where we can
adjust how our color management works in
our project now you can adjust this for
your whole project but some timelines
are going to override the settings with
their timeline settings and that's
what's happening in our case so you can
find all of this stuff here especially
if you haven't made a timeline yet
you're just setting up your project but
we're going to talk about it in the
timeline settings so we can actually see
it happening I'm going to go over to
Media pool and then right click on our
timeline this is our color page start
timeline go to timelines timeline
settings and we have similar settings
here as we do in the project settings if
I go over to color this is going to give
us our color management settings by
default this is set to D Vinci y RGB and
what that means is B basically we're not
doing anything fancy with the color
we're just letting the colors be what
they are which is why we have this kind
of gray washed out footage but we can
switch this from yrgb to Da Vinci yrgb
color managed and click this like this
and there are some other settings that
you can play with but for most things
that you're probably going to do you can
just leave it like that let's go down
and hit
okay and now hey nothing happens so good
wow we did it congratulations but it's
unlocked some background magic here if I
right click on this
clip I now have this little section
added to my context menu where it says
input color space I can go to input
color space and I can select whatever
camera and format I shot by default it's
just going to be Rec 709 for a lot of
shots but I shot this on Blackmagic
design and this is in Blackmagic design
pocket 6K film Gen 4 and you do have to
know that for this to work if you don't
know what log format you're shooting you
need to figure it out look at your
camera get into your menus and figure
out what you're shooting ask the person
who shot it if you didn't shoot your
footage figure it out but there should
be some way to figure out what camera
you shot it on and in what mode so for
me it's Blackmagic design pocket 6K film
Gen 4 there's a bunch of stuff with
Blackmagic design for other ones it's a
little bit easier Canon you're probably
shooting clog you use clog one 2 or
three Sony you probably have slog s log2
or slog 3 again you can find this in the
menus of your camera I'll go to
Blackmagic design pocket 6K film Gen 4
and now look what happens click this and
oh baby oh baby it looks pretty good all
I had to do was tick a box and now all
of that work that I was doing with the
gain and the lift and the saturation and
the gamma all of that is done for me in
fact these were all shot on the same
camera so I can shift select all of
these clips right cck click and go to
input color space black magic
design pocket 6K film Gen 4 and then oh
baby look at this stuff it's looking
pretty good now do these look perfect no
but it doesn't look log anymore right if
I were to right click on this and go to
bypass color management we can see this
log
footage and then this is with the color
management applied so the point of this
is to take your footage from log into
decent looking image it's not a creative
process it's almost like developing your
film you're kind of just converting it
from shooting mode into display mode and
this is really if you're going to do
color correction right this is the first
step this is what you should do first
because now everything that we do in the
nodes everything that we do here is
going to run through that color
management and we're going to get a
better result that's just how it is
because the color science that resolve
is putting onto this footage is designed
to kind of reverse engineer what the
camera was doing to make that gray log
footage and it's going to give us some
pretty nice colors now it's dependent on
how we shot this for instance this looks
pretty good this looks pretty good this
looks kind of crazy it looks pretty wild
that's because we shot this maybe a
little bit bright and so it's not that
you won't need to correct it but any
correction that you'll need to do is
going to look better as it runs through
this color management so for instance I
could take this offset down just to
darken this image a little bit I could
take the saturation down just to take
that wild red off of the screen and now
we have a pretty decent looking shot but
the difference is I only had to do a
couple things take the offset wheel down
take the saturation down if I didn't
have color Management on
go to our timeline settings and switch
this back to D Vinci y RGB if I didn't
have color Management on I would have to
push this gain up push this lift down do
some saturation take the gamma down
maybe add a little bit of a curve do all
this kind of stuff to get a similar
result but it's a lot more work and
honestly uh in my experience it doesn't
look as good so instead I'm just going
to right click and say reset all grades
and nodes you can also hit control home
that's going to reset everything I've
done in this
node go back to our timeline settings
and turn on that color management hit
okay and now we have our kind of bright
looking shot that we can just adjust
real quick and get a pretty good result
same thing here for our handsome boy
maybe we push the gamma up just a little
bit take the saturation down a touch and
we're good and so that's the thing when
you have color Management on it doesn't
take a whole lot to make your shots look
good this one maybe needs a little bit
of exposure which I can just do with the
offset wheel here and we can kind of
just page through and see if there's
anything we need to
change same thing here this is a little
bit bright take the offset down a lot
maybe take the saturation down a touch
again we can make this into a nighttime
shot if we want to but let's say this
was a daytime shot we can adjust that
without a whole lot of work and now I've
went through and this one could maybe be
a little bit brighter maybe a little
more more
contrast but now I've kind of gone
through and made all my shots look
decent and it just didn't take tons of
effort so that's the really big deal
when it comes to color management but
there are a couple different ways to
color manage in resolve this is probably
the easiest way but it's also the way
that kind of does things behind the
scenes that you don't really have any
control over so the color management
that's being applied to this clip it's
hidden away from me I can't see it or
control it or even turn it off or on
really easily I would have to just
bypass it from each
clip and so for me personally I'm not a
huge fan of doing color management this
way if you like it this way that's
totally fine there's nothing wrong with
it as long as you feel comfortable but
I'm going to right click on my timeline
and go over to timeline settings and I'm
going to switch this back to D Vinci
yrgb and then I'll just go ahead and hit
okay now we don't have any color
Management on but we can add it
ourselves and we can do that with a
special node so I'm going to right click
on this node and say add node add serial
and this is going to be our color
management node and I'm just going to
drag this all the way to the end of our
node graph because color management is
something that you're generally going to
want to do at the very end so you put it
on first so that you can see what you're
doing but it actually applies to the
image last so before I do anything I'm
just going to put this node over to the
right I'll right click on it and say no
label and I'm going to call this
CST that stands for color space
transform which is a way to do color
management now up here in the upper
right we have a button that says effects
and this is a lot like our effects panel
in the other pages but one of the
effects here is called color space
transform and I can apply any effect to
any node by just grabbing it from the
effects panel and just dragging it onto
that node specifically so now we have
this color space transform node and we
have a color space transform applied to
it now it's not doing anything right now
because we haven't set the settings and
what we're going to do is tell it the
type of camera and format and everything
that we shot with just like we did in
the timeline settings but we're just
doing it here in the inspector for the
effect controls of this node right so
input color space you got to look that
up for your camera for me it's
Blackmagic design wide gamut gen 45 for
input gamma it's
Blackmagic design pocket 6K film Gen
4 now this is going to make this look
crazy town until we set our output color
space output color space I'm just going
to go down to Rex
709 that's a good color space to pick if
you're going to export to YouTube or to
view on the computer or somebody's phone
it's really what you use for just about
everything just select Rex 79 for both
the color space and the gamma and then
the rest of this is kind of up to your
personal preference it's going to look
fine like this but I like to turn tone
mapping to luminance mapping and gamut
mapping to saturation compression okay
that's as scary as it gets that's all
we're doing and really you can copy my
exact settings here if you want to just
make sure to change the input color
space in the gamma to whatever you're
shooting with whatever camera you used
to shoot this footage okay now we can
close this effects panel keep this CST
at the end and we're essentially doing
the exact same thing that we were doing
in our timeline settings but we can
easily turn this off and on just by
clicking the number here on this
node any node we want we can disable or
enable just by clicking the
number and so we can turn this off and
on and see what's happening and see if
there's any problems or anything like
that we can decide when this happens
there are certain things that you might
want to do after the CST certain
different kinds of effects and
everything you might want to do but
we're in control and we can see that
it's applied right and that's why I like
to do it this way is I like to have just
this node here at the end and what I can
do is set up my nodes exactly how I want
including the CST and I can apply all of
these nodes to everything here in my
project easiest way to do that is just
shift select all of the clips and then
you can middle button Mouse click that's
clicking down on on your scroll wheel on
whatever clip you want to copy those
noes from so I'll copy it from shot n
just click down on my scroll wheel it's
going to ask if you want to replace
existing grades I'll say replace and now
as I go through these different shots we
have our CST on all of the shots and it
looks basically how it did when we had
our color Management on but now it's
really clear that that color management
is happening for each shot and where
it's happening and I can pick this node
before for the color management and
adjust it move things around adjust my
white balance whatever I want to do
before it hits that color management so
how do you pick how do you pick which
one you want to do should I use the CST
or should I go into
timeline settings and do it this way
long story short if you don't really
care to take a lot of control over the
CST I would just right click go to
timelines timeline settings and just
switch this to color managed then you
got to make sure that you select all of
your Clips right click and set that
input color space and if you have
multiple different kinds of cameras you
know you have Sony cameras and the other
ones are Blackmagic or Canon or whatever
you can select just those and turn those
to a different camera than the other
Clips so you can kind of mix those in on
the same timeline if you want to I
always do it with CST CU I like that
control and that's how we're going to be
doing it for the rest of the time but
just know it's it's kind of the same
thing comes down to personal preference
so now that we've learned learned a
little bit about what color management
is and that we'll probably need that on
every clip let's talk about the smartest
way to put this on every clip if you're
not using the project level or timeline
level automatic color management and
you're using a CST node you can put this
CST node or anything else that you want
to apply to a bunch of clips into either
the timeline nodes or the group nodes so
what do I mean by that up here above our
nodes we have two dots and if I switch
to this right dot this switches to our
timeline nodes and check this out if I
select this node anything that ijust in
this node like uh let's just take the
saturation down that applies not only to
this shot but also every shot in the
whole thing and so these are common to
all of the shots on the timeline which
is really great if you are creating a
common look if you want to make
everything black and white this is a
great way to do it you know add some
contrast all of that
kind of thing and so you can add a
common look to every clip in your
timeline just by using the nodes in the
timeline nodes you can switch back by
either clicking this other dot or using
this drop down going back to clip so
again clip only affects the clip that
you're looking at and that is selected
here but there's also a different way to
do this and let's just grab both of
these monster shots I'm just going to
control select both of these and let's
just right click on one of them and go
up to sort of the middle of this menu
and let's select add into new group now
we can make a group name we'll just call
this
alien and hit okay and now both of these
clips that I have selected have these
little chain links that means that
they're in a group together and let's
make another group with our guy here
right click add into new
group we'll just call this
guy now since we have a different group
here when I have this group selected we
have chain links on this clip as well as
any other clip that's in its group if I
select the alien again we just have the
chain links there so it's easy to tell
what else is in the group that way now
let me just go back to timeline real
quick and get rid of this just right
click and say reset node grade go back
to our clip so we don't have that black
and white sometimes this doesn't update
those thumbnails you can always right
click and say update all thumbnails and
that should load the current grades into
all of these thumbnails now once we have
something
grouped we have a couple more dots up
here we have our clip and our timeline
but in between those and kind of before
them is the group pre-cp and the group
post clip now what does that mean well
let me kind of just explain this real
quick with just nodes here in the clip
nodes I'll hit alt s a couple times and
here's how it works we'll call this clip
node
so any shot that you have selected by
default you're adjusting the clip nodes
but if you want to make an adjustment
before the clip nodes you could put
something in the group
pre-cp if you want to adjust something
after the clip nodes this would be group
post clip and then after that comes the
timeline
noes so these flow in order and really
the difference is that in in the clip
nodes you won't see any of these other
adjustments you're only going to see the
nodes that you have inside of the clip
nodes in the group post clip you won't
see any of the other ones just the group
post clip but they happen in this order
so just like here if we were to take
this group pre-cp and make things really
pink and then in the clip nodes
desaturate it and then in the group post
clip make it really blue and then in the
timeline put a whole bunch of contrast
on it all of that stuff would happen in
this order 1 2 3 4 and what we're really
doing is just kind of splitting these
nodes up into pages so if I just select
this and hit contrl + C and then I'll
just hit backspace to get rid of it I
can go to my group pre-cp and hit
control+v and we'll just put that there
on its own page same thing here group
post clip contrl C get rid of this and
put that on group post clip and then
same thing here take our timeline contrl
C
delete and boom there's our timeline
we're going to have the exact same
result here as we did when these were
all in the clip nodes the only
difference is that these are split into
four different pages and three of the
pages this group pre-cp group post clip
and timeline those apply to Clips other
than this clip so I'm just going to
reset all of this stuff so now check
this out if I wanted to do my color
management here I could put that in the
group post clip we'll just copy this CS
T here into our group post
clip and then I have my color management
set up but I don't see the nodes here in
the clip it's just being applied to
whatever I do here in the clip nodes
also this shot right here which happens
to have a CST in the clip nodes that
will get that same CST and so I can run
this through common color management but
I could also go to the group post clip
and I'll hit shift s to add a node
before this color space transform and
let's say maybe this whole group I want
to expose up a little bit so I'll just
push the offset up a little bit maybe I
want to make this a little bit more warm
so I'll push that towards kind of warm
and now this look is applied to not only
shot n but also shot Seven because it's
in the group with it if I go over to the
clip nodes and take the saturation down
for shot N I have this kind of warm
black and white but shot Seven doesn't
have that warm black and white now why
is that because
shot n has this black and white node in
the clip nodes which is just applying to
this clip and shot 7 doesn't have
anything going on so these are unique
even if they're in a group so why all
these different pages and everything
what's what's the point of that if you
can put your color space transform your
color management your look in the
timeline why do you need to make groups
well sometimes you might want to have
different color management for a
different camera or a different scene
sometimes you might have some kind of
different piece of video that doesn't
need color corrected and it's easier to
manage that with groups because if you
have something applying to the entire
timeline you're applying that to
everything in the timeline that means
even graphics and everything that you've
brought in and you really don't want to
color correct Graphics that you've
brought in most of the time so what I'll
do even if I have just a bunch of the
same camera is I'll usually justr a
select everything right
click go up to groups add into a new
group and we'll just call this main or
something like that that'll add
everything into the same group and we'll
set up our color management here in the
group post clip I'll get rid of this
timeline
grade and I'll just select everything
down here right click in the blank space
and say reset all grades and nodes
that's only going to reset the grades in
the
clips the group post clip is only going
to reset if you have that up while you
right click and say
reset but all the clips just have the
default empty node here with nothing
going on but we have our color space
transform set up in our group post clip
we can do more stuff after that in the
timeline if we want to but we're really
set up well to color grade our movie now
and this is so exciting because now it's
just a matter of making sure the shots
look good together and make sense and
we've done a lot of the technical work
and now it's getting just a little bit
more subjective and a little bit more
creative so let's talk worklow if we're
going to color correct our whole scene
and we want it all to feel balanced and
all to feel like it was all shot at the
same time and look really nice how do we
go about doing that well there are a few
different techniques for that but I
think my favorite is called the hero
shot technique and really what it is is
you pick a shot that you like that has a
lot of common elements in it one that
you feel like is representative of the
scene and you make that shot look good
then you match all of the other shots to
it so let's just start out with making
this shot look good let's go with shot
five I like this shot it's nice to pick
a wide shot because we have both
characters here we have a good idea of
what the curtains look like what the
walls look like how bright everything is
how bright the couch is what color
everything is and so it's going to be
great when we go over to our next shot
and we have similar things we can match
all the other colors
with this shot now if you shot this well
and exposed it well and everything this
shouldn't be quite as hard but no matter
how good of a job you did you'll
probably have to make some kind of
tweaks to make these match either way
let's start with this clip and really
we're going to start with asking what is
wrong with this what's something that we
don't like about it is there anything we
can fix or change or make better one
thing I'd say is this is actually
supposed to be set at night and this was
shot during the day and so we should
probably add a little contrast here we
should probably do something to make
this look a little bit more like a
nighttime shot and before we get too
crazy on adjusting this shot I'd really
like to kind of set up our creative look
so let's go over to our group post clip
and before our CST I'll hit shift s and
let's just label this and we'll call
this
look and there are a lot of different
tools here in the color page to help us
make creative looks so far we've really
only learned about the primary color
wheels but another tool that I think is
super helpful is the curves the curves
is a graph of the input versus the
output brightnesses of the image down in
the lower left is black up in the upper
right is white and in the middle is gray
so if we were going to take the input
which is along the x axis and regra it
to the output of the y- axis we could
take the middle of this and just push it
up that's going to make the midle middle
brightnesses brighter and so this is
just kind of pushing up those midtones
right if we bring it down that's going
to make the middle tones
darker same thing for the highlights if
we were going to take the highlights
down we can push this down like this and
we can't really push it up but we can
kind of push it up into the left which
is going to do kind of the same thing
it's making it brighter same thing for
the darkest parts we can take that push
that down like that so we have a lot of
control over our image just like we
would with lift gamma and gain by using
either the bottom the top or the middle
of this graph but what's cool is you can
grab a couple of points on this graph or
even change them around a bunch and you
can get some really interesting types of
contrast and really interesting exposure
adjustments here that are based on all
different tones of the image okay so one
thing that I like to do is maybe take
the highlights down just a little bit
and take the Shadows up just a little
bit and then add a little S curve like
this this tends to make things look just
a little bit nicer so now we look at our
shot here it is before and here's after
so we're just adding a little bit of
subtle contrast and it's really
easy and of course you want to look at
it and make sure that you feel like you
like it but that's a nice little
contrast curve to put into that it's
always a good place to start and you
don't have to be this subtle you could
definitely like push this down a little
more make this a little bit more Moody
it really depends on the mood of your
scene you don't want to push it down way
too much or it's just not going to look
realistic but you want it to be subtly
informing the feeling of the
scene okay so we can have something
maybe like that just get some nice
contrast there maybe we can push up some
of the brighter parts and kind of mess
with this until feel like it looks nice
you can try this without it or with it
and I definitely think it looks better
with it let's actually rename this let's
call this a
contrast and I'll make another node
before this and we can label this
something else let's just call this um
Color cast maybe we want this whole
thing to feel a little bit cooler so we
can take this temperature and just bring
it a little bit to the left and that's
going to make this feel like it's more
nighttime see that oh that's looking so
much better we're just adding a little
bit of blue to these outsides we have a
little bit of blue outside here and this
is just making it feel more like it's
nighttime right that just feels a lot
better and so we can go crazy on look
building and everything that's a whole
crazy art in itself but the big idea
here is you're going to want to make
sure that your colors look good and are
doing a nice job to every clip that
they're applied to now some of these
clips are going to need some adjustment
but you want to make sure that you're
not doing something just totally crazy
to any of these clips and that they
still look somewhat reasonable or else
you're going to just be fighting this
the whole time you know if you make
everything blue but like everything
except for this shot is way too blue and
you're always taking out blue there's no
point in doing that you might as well
just make this less blue and then add a
little more blue to this shot you want
to make sure that 70 or 80% of what
you're doing is going to be just fine
for your shots and if it's not hurting
anything it looks better on than off
then you're in a good spot okay let's go
back to our hero shot here and I'm going
to switch back over to my clip now at
this point our shots looking better but
we do need a little bit of work feels
like it's maybe underexposed feels like
it might need a little bit more
adjustment here so let's take this
offset and just push this up a little
bit and I'm going to call this node just
exposure and I'm going to make a new
node and this is just so that we can
break up what we're doing into Little
Steps and we can turn each step on and
off okay let's make this node
saturation and
temperature this we're going to play
around with the color temperature see if
we want this to be a little bit more
cool or a little warmer I think I maybe
just a touch more cool is
fine we could also see if it's better
saturated a little more we could have
some really bright colors like that or
we could take it down desaturate it I'm
thinking somewhere in there looks pretty
good so maybe just a touch of saturation
so here's before and here's after very
very
subtle we see a little bit here on the
curtains and that might be all this shot
really
needs we might decide we like it we
might want to get a little bit more
detailed later maybe pop the yellow on
these lamps or something like that but
we can do that after we get things
mostly dialed in it's a really good idea
to work in passes and this is true for
just about anything when you're creating
a video um but it's especially to color
grading we've really done one big pass
which is our color space transform so
you know even some of these shots are
probably too dark or too bright or
whatever but they all have the color
Management on it right throughout our
whole movie which happens to be a really
short movie but the idea is that you
would go through your whole scene kind
of
holistically you make sure it looks
pretty good overall cuz like if I were
to show someone this shot I wouldn't be
ashamed of it it looks pretty good it's
not perfect it's not exactly how I would
want to presentent it in an ideal world
but it's it's okay and what we really
want to do is get everything to this
point get everything to okay as fast as
possible and then we can go in and tweak
things and so let's just right click on
this and say grab
still and then up here in the upper left
we can click on our gallery and this is
where we can save stills from our shots
and it's interesting that they call this
a still because while it is a screenshot
of this image it it's also a preset so
it's it's kind of funny if you
rightclick and you go to display node
graph it also keeps all of the
information for your color grade inside
of this still and so they should really
call it like a a preset or a template or
something but it also has a still frame
of your
shot and so you can go to another shot
and then you could right click on this
still and say Play Still and what it'll
do is it'll will give you this little
wipe and so you can play your footage
and look at this still as a
reference which is really helpful for
trying to match different elements right
so now we have our guy here and this is
about how light he is of course this is
the shadow side of his face but he's
kind of warmer we can see the walls are
kind of warm the couch is kind of this
warmish green and by comparing these we
can see that this shot is definitely a
little bit too cool it's a little bit
too blue whereas if we were to look at
the shot by
ourself our eyes kind of get used to it
and we go yeah I mean that looks good it
looks good by itself but it doesn't
really match with this shot and so what
we're doing is we're going to match
everything to this shot so that's why we
picked this clip that has you know the
blanket in there that we can match this
blanket to it has lamps that we can
match this lamp too has walls and pretty
much all of the elements that are in the
other shots we can kind of match to this
still so let's do the easy one first the
one that's just a different take of this
one and if we want to copy our color
grade we can just middle button Mouse
click that's click down on our scroll
wheel and if we did it right we should
barely be able to see the difference
here all right that works pretty good
obviously people are in different spaces
but the colors are nearly identical so
that's great and then let's also copy
this to this shot and then let's go to
shot two which is going to be probably
different but let's try out that same
grade a middle button Mouse click and
man that's pretty close that's pretty
close that just about works I would
say I would say maybe there's just a
little bit more green in this shot and
so we could go to our saturation
temperature
node we could maybe push this tint away
from Green just a little bit and maybe
towards blue just a
touch and see if
that tends to work better and we're
never going to get a absolutely perfect
match but these should both feel like
they live in the same world there
shouldn't be some big change because
nobody's ever going to see these side by
side like this but we want them to feel
like they live in the same world and
that these two things were shot at the
same time they're happening in the same
moment even if they don't look 100%
perfect they should look you know 95%
perfect 95% there think I might go a
little less crazy on the green maybe
like three three or
four the exposure is about right the
colors are about right I'd say maybe we
could take the exposure up just a
touch I think that
works one piece of advice is don't spend
too long trying to guess this usually
your very first impression is probably
about right because your eyes get used
to things and you kind of start to
justify things and so it's a good idea
to just keep moving especially at the
matching stage right so we have shots 5
8 and 11 matched two looks pretty good
let's look at
three three looks maybe a little bit
dark and a little bit Green Let's middle
button Mouse click here copy that over
now that just makes it a little bit too
bright I would
say maybe let's take the offset down
just a touch maybe push up the gamma a
little bit just to give it a little bit
of midtones and again I think it's just
maybe a little greenish and maybe not
quite cool enough so we can take the
saturation temperature take the
temperature down a little bit that
really helps look at that that's a big
big difference that really helps could
maybe just take a tiny bit of green out
too yes and if we're matching both of
these to the same reference they should
actually match pretty well together too
and that's that's the idea right is if
we switch in between these it shouldn't
feel super weird this one's maybe just a
little bit bright still so I might just
take even take the gain down a little
bit take the gamma up a
touch yeah that looks pretty good I
would say kind of switch in between
these yeah looks good now there are some
problems like this backpack looks really
red again we can kind of fix this later
we're looking for the great big obvious
problems here okay now let's go to his
shot here again this is just way too
blue let's middle button Mouse click
this
this grade and I don't know this might
be farther off than we really want to be
I'm just going to right click and reset
node grade for each of these nodes and I
would say the exposure is maybe just a
little bright so take that down just a
touch just in the offset and then in
saturation temperature we'll actually
bring this a little bit further away
from
Blue and we're looking at the color of
his face we're also looking at the
highlights in this couch matching him
with the highlights in this couch and
his face that's looking a little better
would
say see maybe push this towards green
Just a Touch
Too there we go that's looking a lot
better I can select these and hit
control D to deselect them so here's
where we were and here's where we are
now one thing I want to look at is this
exposure I feel like it's a little bit
dark right here so I can take this lift
and just push this up a touch
it's going to lighten that just a little
bit I can kind
of counteract that with the gamma could
maybe even mess with the curves a little
bit push that lift up just a touch push
the gain down a little bit just kind of
take some of that contrast
out just so we don't plunge too far into
black there when you decrease the
contrast and something sometimes you
have to push a little bit more
saturation into it we kind of just work
this image around until it matches with
the other one and that feels pretty good
to me okay shot 10 going to middle
button Mouse click on six and that's
going to be the same thing so now we
have a lot of these match the only thing
that's a really big deal is this
backpack reason this backpack is really
different is we had different lighting
we had different exposure this was shot
like 3 weeks later um because we didn't
get a shot of the backpack here when we
were in this house and we don't have any
reference to the backpack in our
reference image but we can bring up
maybe this image and I'll right click
and say grab still and then we can go
over to our gallery and click on the
backpack image and play still like that
and now we have some reference that we
can look at with the purple blanket as
hands this kind of thing so one thing
that definitely needs to happen is we
need to take this exposure down and
probably take the saturation way
down maybe not so much the exposure but
definitely take down the the saturation
same thing with the lift let's push the
lift up this almost seems like this
might even be shot with a different
color profile or something I mean it's
just really different so one thing we
could try is just rightclick let's add
into a new
group let's call this alien
CST this time here in our group post
clip I'll just copy and paste our stuff
but we're going to change our CST I'm
going to make three notes just like this
and I can control C this CST node and
I'll contrl C and contrl V the contrast
and contrl c and control V the color
cast that's going to give us the same
treatment but let's take this color
space transform and let's see if maybe
we shot this with a
different different thing did we shoot
with um a video Gen
5 video Gen4 maybe see that's feeling
actually a little bit more
reasonable that looks like it's
almost matching better yeah I think we
might have shot this in the wrong color
space so this is a great reason to use
groups is you can just easily take that
out so let's switch back over here and
now let's work on this and this is much
much less fighting than we had so one
big thing is maybe I'll take the
exposure down just a
touch I feel like it might be just a
little magenta here so we could take
just push a little bit of green into it
we'll call this
exposure and then in this next node
let's call this U sat temp we'll take
this and maybe push a little more green
going to go way too far then kind of
bring it
back just to where that's starting to
feel
reasonable maybe push it a little bit
cool this purple and this red maybe feel
just a little
bit closer to where they
were and if we want to get really crazy
about the purple later we can do that we
are going to take some of the red down
in the other Clips but okay so this
looks pretty good we can probably copy
and paste this to the other shots but
first we're going to take these shots
out of our group and put them into the
alien CST group we just going to go to
groups pick the group you want and then
say assign to group that's going to
assign those to the new group and then
we'll also middle button Mouse click to
copy over the clip
nodes okay this guy is looking a lot
better now
so much better yeah that's reasonable
look at that so we have all of this
matching together pretty
well and the only thing we're not going
to worry about matching so much is going
to be this outside shot which again is a
day for night shot and so let's just do
the same kind of work we did on the
other ones let's do exposure and let's
do saturation
temp so exposure just going to roll down
on my offset quite a bit just take this
way way
down something like that take the gain
down gamma up a little bit saturation in
temp let's take the saturation down a
touch and I'm just going to take the
offset towards blue quite a bit just so
we're starting to kind of feel like this
is nighttime we can add
some some contrast
here push the lift up it's almost kind
of a reminder that this is a nighttime
shot we'll need a little bit more work
on this but we can get that kind of
roughed in
so now we have all of our clips and it's
a good idea at this point to play
through it and just make sure that you
like what things are looking like this
one I think might just need to be a
little warmer and maybe take the gamma
down just a touch it's hard to tell when
you're just looking right at an image
but you cut in between that can really
help okay let's go with that see how
that
works and as this plays back you'll
notice problems and if you don't notice
problems then it's probably close enough
enough and you don't need to worry about
it tooo
much yeah that's working well swims may
be a little dark but not too bad so
there we have kind of the first major
pass of our scene we've learned quite a
bit about nodes and groups some tips on
matching shots and we've mostly been
using the primary color wheels and the
curves next we'll get into some
secondary Corrections so now that we
have our scene balanced let's get a
little bit more detailed and this is
where resolve just really does some cool
stuff let's just go to shot six just so
we can talk about some of this stuff H
shot 10 because then it's a slightly
less
awkward kind of face all right so far
everything that we've done has applied
to the entire image so for instance if I
make another serial node here if I push
up the offset everything in the image
gets brighter or darker if I push
anything towards pink pretty much
everything goes pink and none of this is
limited to any kind of part of this
image but we have a lot of tools to be
able to control not just the image as a
whole but little pieces of the image
both either certain colors or certain
brightnesses certain saturations or even
certain places on screen like physical
spaces and there are a lot of tools for
this one tool that I really like are the
more kind of advanced curves and so here
we have a bunch of different little
icons here and if I click through these
this will give you what a lot of people
call the hsl curves stands for Hue
saturation and luminance and instead of
remapping the brightnesses of our image
we're selecting colors based on their
Hue and then adjusting them by clicking
little points on this line and moving
them up and down if you've ever used
like an equalizer for audio this is a
very similar kind of concept and so for
instance we have this kind of blue here
which we can see as a spike here on our
histogram and if I make a couple of
points here and then take this point and
move it up and down we can see that it
changes the Hue of that blue in the
background and it pretty much leaves his
face and the red shirt and everything
unchanged and so this is a really nice
gentle way to move colors around a
little bit and so you can get pretty
detail
you know if we don't like that blue we
can make that a different color or just
reset this here we can switch over to
Hue versus saturation which I think a
little bit more useful and we can put
our control points here we could also
just select kind of a preset like this
sort of light blue that's going to make
three control points and we can move the
middle one like that we could also click
here on our image and that will make
control points pretty much where we want
to be so let's just take this and let's
say we want to desaturate this blue
because we don't want it to be that
bright blue can take this and just bring
it down like that look at that all of a
sudden we have what looks like a much
more balanced image and all we're doing
is just taking away that blue so that's
a really nice way to adjust a specific
color in the color page of
resolve and there are different versions
of this there's Hue versus Hue Hue
versus saturation luminance which you
know you can select a certain Hue and
then brighten it or darken it and this
can get you in trouble a little bit it's
easier to Break um and make the image
look bad then we have luminance versus
saturation so depending on how bright
something is you can make it more
saturated or less saturated same thing
for how saturated something is so this
is great if you have something that's
overs saturated so for instance shot 4
we could take this and as things get
more saturated we can push them down and
be less saturated and so this is a nice
way to kind of limit the saturation of
things just using a curve so we're not
really desaturating most of the rest of
the image but the really saturated stuff
we're bringing back down and of course
you can be a little bit more choosy
about how saturated things can go kind
of depends on what you're looking for
but this can solve a lot of problems we
also have saturation versus luminance
things that are more saturated we can
kind of darken so something that's like
here we can just darken that a little
bit or brighten it and that's going to
change the way our picture looks
and so you have tons of control here in
the curves we'll go back to shot 10 here
another tool that's sort of similar to
these Hue curves would be the color
warper now this is I mean really kind of
a similar concept it's just built kind
of around a circle and so let's say we
want to make his lips really saturated
here I can click on his lips and that's
going to select the nearest control
Point here and so I can take this and I
can move it further away from the center
to make it more saturated or closer to
this Center to make it less saturated
and I can move it around the circle
we'll just make this a little bit bigger
so we can see it I can move this around
the circle to change the Hue itself and
what's really neat is I can actually
click and drag directly on the image
like this and as I click and drag it's
like I'm clicking and dragging in the
color warper but I can stay right on the
image so depending on how many control
points I have here so maybe I want just
a lot this is kind of an easy way to
break your image having all these
control points but you can also get
really detailed so I can take these lips
and I can kind of push them out like
that to make those a little bit brighter
I can take his skin and move it in to
make it a little bit less saturated I
can take this blue and move that in to
make that less saturated and I can do
all of this just by kind of clicking and
dragging and I can get a really
interesting look here just with one tool
let's say I want take these lips and
change their color I can kind of push
that around now he has pink
lipstick oh so many things I could do
but this color warper is a really nice
tool and I think I'll just reset this
and turn this back down to
6x6 because this is also a great tool
for kind of adjusting your look and what
I like to do is go into a shot like this
and sometimes I'll just use this um
sometimes even just just on the group
post clip uh as creating a look so we
can just do like a shift space bar here
and you can take away or shift some of
the colors that are in your image like
for instance this kind of yellowish
green a lot of the time I don't really
want that yellowish green so I can take
this yellowish green and kind of just
push it in and it sort of clarifies the
colors that are there same thing for
this kind of pinkish purple I could
bring that in and you don't see a lot of
difference here but as we turn this off
and on it just kind of takes away that
nasty green BL tone and it just makes
everything feel a little bit more pure
we're just kind of desaturating the
colors that aren't as prominent and it
just makes it look clearer we can take
things that are royal blue like this and
then push those a little bit more cyan
same thing for green we could push that
a little bit more cyan and so we can
kind of create this color palette just
with the color warper and it's just a
fantastic way to work so easy and man it
makes things look good if you just if
you're subtle with it if you're careful
with it you do it right now we can go
through and now we have sort of this uh
kind of teal and orangish look on our
image that we didn't really have before
right and depending on how much you like
that you can keep that or not it's maybe
making his skin a little bit pink so
maybe we can take this more towards
orange and see if that helps a little
bit that definitely feels a little
better and we kind of go through our
shots this is again this is something
you should probably do before you go
through and color correct all of your
shots but the color warper is a great
great tool for this kind of thing so I
don't know maybe we'll leave that on
there I do like it so we'll just call
this um color palette call
pallet call pal now we have this much
more kind of clarified look really like
that that looks nice so yeah color
warper is great there's a lot of
different things you can do with the
color warper I mean we could have a
whole course on just the color warper
but we got other stuff to get into to
here another tool is the qualifier now
the qualifier is sometimes used for
similar things that we've kind of been
working with for instance a lot of
people will kind of grab somebody's skin
grab the skin tones on the skin you can
think of this as kind of like a green
screen key and what you're really doing
is just selecting certain colors in the
image which you can kind of preview with
this little button up here this we just
put this on Gray and as I select the
different colors it's going to show me
the selection here and so if I just want
a skin color I can kind of go over that
that's going to pick just his skin color
and then I can take this and whatever I
do is only going to happen inside of
that selection and so you know if I make
this crazy blue it's only going to
happen to the parts that are selected
and we can adjust the selections here we
can select a smaller range of hue and
move that around to adjust our selection
soften it and that kind of thing and
obviously this is a huge correction that
we wouldn't make but you can kind of
start to see see the problem with this
uh the big thing is that you don't
always get a really clean selection
sometimes you get noise and stuff that's
happening and it's really hard to make
something look natural by selecting
colors and adjusting them this way and
so if you can stay away from it I would
probably recommend just staying away
from the qualifier unless you have a
really specific reason to only use the
qualifier one reason might be if you
were going to do something that wasn't
just a color shift uh you know something
that you could do in the curves like a
hue saturation or luminance change if
it's something like you're going to blur
something like if you're going to do
something like select his skin and then
do that trick where you take the midtone
detail down so what we could do is just
select his skin like this again we'll
look at the selection I can switch this
to black and white mode too and we can
change our Center change our width and
we're just going to try and select his
face mostly I'll turn on saturation in
luminance soften this a little bit we're
going to try and get the best selection
of his face kind of blur that a little
bit and you can go in here to this mat
finesse here and you can change your mat
and basically you're trying to get a
good selection just like you would for
something like a green screen something
like that you can clean the white which
stands for the part that you're
selecting you clean the black which is
the part that you're getting rid of and
you can make this kind of crazy
selection you can push that pre- filter
up and that that'll help a little bit
and now we have his skin roughly
selected here right and so if I turn off
our highlight nothing's happened so far
because all we've done is just tell this
node exactly where to do whatever we're
going to have it do and we haven't
really told it to do anything yet we've
just made a selection and so now if I
take this Hue I can move this around and
I can give him purple skin if I want to
that kind of thing but where this is
really helpful is if we go to one of
these other tabs so like this Blur tab
we could push the radius up on the blur
and that can blur his skin a little bit
or maybe a little bit better idea would
be to take this midtone detail down so
you take the midtone de detail down and
that kind of softens his face a little
bit and you would have to do some more
work to get a really good mat cuz we
don't really want to soften his eyes or
anything you can make somebody look a
little bit younger by doing this kind of
thing kind of refining their face like
this and in the paid version of resolve
there are automated tools and stuff for
this one's called face refinement but
this is really the only case that I
would consider using a qualifier for
just because you have to work so hard to
get a good selection that I mean if you
can do it with the curves I would really
recommend you do it with the curves okay
now another way that we can select
different aspects of our image is just
with the physical space like you know
the left side or the right side of the
frame we can do that with a window this
fourth icon over is window and you can
think of a window as just like a mask
kind of like infusion whatever we're
doing in this node to only happen inside
of a circle we can click this circle
thing and it will make a circle and
whatever we do is only going to happen
inside of that Circle and we can combine
something like the qualifier where we're
just selecting his skin and we can limit
that qualifier to just the circle and we
can have a little bit better result for
our
adjustment let's just reset this node
and let's say we want to darken this
side of the shot we could put a window
on this node we could just use a circle
window or whatever window we want and
these little handles here is how soft
the selection is so if I just push this
really blue just so we can see it if I
take this down and turn off our overlay
here we can see that this Edge is a
little bit crisper but if I turn on the
power window overlay and kind of push
this up we'll see it kind of Fades out
and this right here is probably the most
valuable tool for secondary Corrections
is a big soft Circle window because
there's a lot you can do with it if I
want to darken the side of this shot I
can just put my big soft Circle window
over here just make it even bigger make
it even softer and then I can just bring
down the offset take that down a little
bit and guess what nobody's ever going
to know that I put a window over there
but look at that difference nobody's
ever going to know that because it's big
and soft right if I want to add a little
bit more brightness to his face I could
add a big soft Circle window here put it
roughly over his face and then push the
offset right push the gain take down the
gamma whatever we want to do and I can
just add a little bit of brightness to
his face that way so this is a great way
you can kind of relight things in
resolve just using a big soft Circle
window now there are other windows I'll
just turn this off for a minute one of
them being like a pen tool so you could
draw your own shape like that but again
a lot of the time you want these really
soft and so you don't generally need to
be this exact with your windows cuz
you're going to want this soft anyway
you just go down here to the softness
controls and push inside and outside up
like this and then we have the same kind
of controls so unless you're going to
have a really irregular shape I probably
wouldn't worry about drawing your own
shape like this it's going to look
roughly the same as if you were to draw
a circle window and it takes less time
to draw a big soft Circle window than it
does to make your own selection right
boom kind of the same deal we also have
a gradient window that's my favorite and
it's fully on on the flat side of the
line and then it fades out along the
arrow and so again if I wanted to darken
this side I could kind of just fade it
off like that reset this and just take
the offset down we have a similar kind
of thing so it kind of depends on what
you want to do but these windows control
where the node does its stuff and so you
could have 10 different things happening
in one node so you know you could have
something where we desaturate Blues
completely we could have something with
you know that pushes down the offset
makes everything a little bit warmer we
have some color warper stuff I mean you
could do a bunch of different stuff in
this node that is what makes it
different than the fusion node is you
have a bunch of stuff you can do it's
just kind of a group of all of the
corrections you're doing down here but
once you add either a qualifier or a
window it changes where the node does
its job and so if we were to switch to
this highlight mode we can see that the
node's really only being applied where
it's white here and then as it fades out
and gets black we're not really touching
the image at all and so if I were to
turn this off we see it's only affecting
things on the left side of the image so
you have a lot of control a lot of
creativ
over how you want to adjust your images
now let me show you something really
cool let's say we want to make him seem
like he has a black eye we could take a
circle window we just put it over his
eye like this just kind of rotate it
like that and often times what I'll do
when I don't want to see the outline of
this window is I'll just switch to the
curves palette and that'll just hide
that window but again because we have
this node selected anything that we do
in the color palettes down here is is
only going to happen inside of that
window so we could take the offset down
a little bit like this maybe take the
gamma down and we'll push the gamma a
little bit warm now he has this kind of
black eye but once this starts moving
because remember we're color grading
video here look at what's happening it's
sliding on his face it's not really
staying on his face and so when it comes
to a window you can always track a
window to kind of stick to whatever you
have it over and
it's pretty amazing the things you can
do in the color page like check this out
I'll make this a little bit bigger just
so it has a little bit more room to
think and I'll switch over to the
tracker page and then check this out
I've done nothing literally just put
this over his eye and watch
this it like perfectly tracks to his
face and even tracks in 3D space like it
sticks to his face this is a really
typical result for window tra in in the
color page it's just absolutely so
dialed in so good and now when we kind
of move this back and turn off this
overlay play this back you absolutely
can't even tell that we messed with his
eye it's just perfect and the softer the
window the easier it is and the more
subtle your correction the easier it is
but look at this even even this if I
were to take this softness down a lot
like this and I order to take this
offset down a lot so we can just really
see that difference check out how good
this is anyway I mean it's stupid like
I'm worried about what black magic did
to make this happen like is it is it
like a is it like actual black magic is
that is that what's going on here I
don't know and also notice this I've
already tracked this but I can still
change this around and I can change its
size and its shape and even its position
and it still moves relative to that
track which is pretty cool and so it's
really easy the color page to just
select part of your image and track that
color grade onto it so cool so now going
back to our day for night shot we know a
little bit more about how things work in
the color page and we could do some more
fancy stuff so for instance I could say
alt s and I could draw a mask just kind
of like we did in the fusion page here
for our sky and we'll just soften that
selection out a little bit just soften
it out and then I could take my curves
let's say and I could bring down the sky
and really make a big difference here
and have it look pretty natural let's
say I want to add those lights back in
kind of like we did in Fusion I can make
a new node but this time I'm going to
add a layer node and what this does is
it will take any input just like
infusion and it will lay this entire
image over what whatever we have here
using this little node here it's kind of
backwards because the lower parts are
actually the upper layers and so here's
the original footage and I can just use
a window here and just make a little
selection with my circle window to add
some of that light back in again soft
Circle does wonders and if I want to add
another window and kind of have multiple
windows affecting the same node I can
just either click on a different kind of
window here here and just add more or I
can go up to here where it says plus
Circle can add another circle like this
and again really soft looking thing like
that another Circle and so you can
really make the argument like wow you
could do quite a bit of kind of
compositing things right here in the
color page even if you don't want to
jump into Fusion very very powerful page
so now we have our lights on and it
looks it looks pretty good maybe we want
to put a little more saturation in in
there it's looking pretty nice really
depends on how crazy we want to get and
then of course if this shot were moving
we could track each of those windows and
that kind of thing but since it's locked
down our life is a little bit easier
that's nice so you can spend as much
time as you want making this look like a
night shot I'm going to open my Clips
again let's just go through and see if
there's anything that we want to change
just with some secondaries there's no
real rules here you can hit alt s and
then let's just label
this secondary and you can have lots and
lots of secondaries you don't have to
have just one in fact it's a good idea
to run secondaries in parallel nodes so
like for instance we might have a node
here let's just say for whatever reason
we want this side to be really blue just
for an example you know a little bit
higher contrast for whatever reason if
we were to make another serial node
after this this is just a node that runs
in series one after another and then you
know make this really yellow and
saturated and that kind of thing these
it mix together and make green and it
doesn't look you know really natural but
we can make this a parallel node instead
and right click and say add node add
parallel and I'm just going to contrl C
and contrl V this right here and then
get rid of it and this can sometimes
give us a little bit more natural result
how these parallel nodes mix together so
here this is
as parallel I'll grab a still here we
are as a cal and let's play that still
and the difference is really subtle but
there is a difference in running one in
parallel and one is not this one looks a
little bit more yellow this one looks a
little bit more green again you could
probably color grade like a 100
different images and maybe not have any
problem with running these in Cal like
that but it's generally safer to do
these secondaries in parallel
and if you're like what the heck what
the heck does parallel even mean why
would I use that I don't I don't
understand the big deal it's really not
that important if you if you don't see
the big deal and you want to be safe do
it this way if you'd rather just keep
things simple and put them in series
that's okay too and again it's just
picking things that we want to change
about the image and just getting a
little bit more detailed this time right
so maybe it's something where we want
these lamps to be a little bit warmer
again big circle window
push the offset a little warmer like
that that help kind of warm up the lamps
so here's before here's after and you
don't want to go like super crazy like
this that doesn't look realistic you
know but you can go a little bit you
know little subtle things all of those
kind of add up to be a big difference
and you can hit up and down on the
keyboard by the way to go in between
clips and go up and down on Clips like
this so what I like to do is just kind
of close my clips and kind of go up and
down make sure that they all look good
so here's definitely a problem for
secondaries this red versus the other
red let's go ahead and grab a still of
this shot and then we can play it here
see if we can kind of match these Reds
this red actually looks pretty good at
this point but it's kind of bright on
this shot so maybe we'll take this shot
and just select the red of our backpack
with a soft window and then we'll
actually change the red with some curve
so we'll probably just use like Hue
versus saturation we can kind of just
drag over this red and now I can take
the red saturation down a little bit
just to kind of calm that down so it
goes from Electric to normal yes this
looks pretty good too that works a
little better this shot I feel like the
lamps could be a little bit warmer so
again we can just do these kind of soft
Circle Windows maybe even take the
temperature just a little warmer like
that again big soft Windows let you get
away with lots we'll just add another
window here another Circle nice big and
soft this now we're changing our lamps
from kind of whitish blue to nice and
yellow same thing here let's say this
blue is just a little bit too crazy we
can again just use the Hue versus
saturation curves and just desaturate
that blue a little bit do the same thing
on shot 10 shot Eight's the same as shot
five so I could middle button Mouse
click here to warm up those lights same
for shot 11 it's a little better maybe
we feel like the blue on this curtain is
a little much I can make another node
we'll call this
curtain and I could probably use like a
gradient and I'll just fade that out
like this we could take the saturation
down a touch maybe take the offset down
a little bit just to darken that side we
don't want to take it down way too much
to where these blacks are just way too
dark we'll just keep it taste here just
something maybe a little closer to that
so here's before and here's after we're
just darkening that down a little bit
feel like the light coming in here is
just way too bright so again we can make
another serial node we could take a soft
window like this and again just maybe
take this offset down a little bit just
darken that a touch the only thing it's
going to be the only thing is it's going
to be a problem when she walks in front
of it and so we could do something like
animate a window over here that kind of
holds this Darkness out so the way to do
that would be to add another Circle but
here we have these little options and if
we click on these like blinds option
like this that will subtract this circle
window from our original selection so we
can kind of minus that so let's just
soften this out and we'll put this over
her so it's just not quite as crazy and
we might just be able to track this I'll
just hit contrl T to track that's the
same as just going here and clicking
this track forward button just hit
control T to track forward and it kind
of sticks to the side of her like that
which isn't quite what we want so it
might just be easier to not track it we
could maybe turn off 3D let's try that
no that doesn't quite work either so
this is kind of one of those situations
where H tracking might actually not work
mostly cuz she's just turning around 180
so what we could do is animate this way
to do that would be just to go to where
we want this to start and then over here
on the right we have this key frames
panel I can click this and I can click
on any of these key frame diamonds for
whichever node I want and so this is
node five so I can go over to node 5 and
just click on automatic key framing
right here and now I'm just going to
touch whatever I want to adjust so I'm
just going to move this to where I want
it and it's going to add a little key
frame there now we're going to move over
a little bit let's just say to like here
just going to move that over to where
it's supposed to be and look it adds
these little arrows that means that it's
animating in between these and now if we
go in between see it kind of moves this
subtly that way then we're going to move
this towards the end of the shot rotate
it put it where it's supposed to be and
I'm just going to check this kind of
throughout the shot and this doesn't
have to be as crazy as you know what we
would do if we were compositing because
again we're using big soft Windows okay
and once I have the basic motion I'm
going to turn off this automatic key
framing thing and that's going to keep
that movement just in the pan and tilt
and rotate of my transform for my window
here so now if I turn off my window
outlines we don't see anything crazy but
look at this difference we're making
we're really darkening that side but
because we use soft windows and we're
just animating those along you don't see
any difference you don't see anything
weird so you can kind of go through and
do some fancy stuff like that too
there's so much stuff you can do in the
color page when it comes to getting
detailed like this so much fun let's
also take a second and talk about color
Scopes color Scopes are a way to measure
the actual colors in an image it's
really easy to look at an image and kind
of have your eyes start to play tricks
on you your eyes will kind of get used
to an image and it won't look so blue
anymore it won't look so saturated
anymore even like a log image after a
while you look at this and you go you
know it looks pretty good because your
eyes kind of get used to it but the
Scopes will always tell you the real
deal they're down here in the lower
right and I'm going to click this expand
button just so that we can talk about
Scopes a little bit and in resolve there
are four main Scopes the parade the
waveform the vector scope and the
histogram for a minute I'm just going to
focus on one of them I'm just going to
click on this one scope thing switch
this to waveform and there's some
options here I'm going to switch this
just to Y and turn off
colorize this is going to help me just
explain Scopes a little bit this
waveform scope is just a graph of the
brightness of the pixels versus their
position horizontally and so if it's on
the left side of the screen it's on the
left side of the graph if it's bright
it's towards the top of the graph if
it's dark it's towards the bottom on the
left side of the screen we have some
darker pixels here and some even darker
pixels here in the couch and this wall
right here we can see is right here on
the waveform I know that because it's
about this much of the screen it's on
the left and it's you know kind of
Darker
grayish bluish a little under middle
brightness and so it's easy to figure
out that's where this is then we have
the stuff in the couch kind of the
darkest parts of the couch are right
here that's going to be this little
divot right here and as we go across the
frame we can see the different
brightnesses of things across the frame
and so the wave form tells you how
bright things are zero being totally
black 1023 being totally white versus
their position horizontally in the frame
now I have this on a certain mode just
so that we can explain this a little
better but you can also show the
waveform in RGB mode and you can
colorize it and what this does is it
makes three different waveforms one for
each Channel red green and blue and so
you can kind of see where the color
casts are in the frame so towards the
left we have stuff that's this
brightness but the blue Channel and the
green channel are higher than the red
Channel which means that this is going
to look sort of cyan and of course it
does look cyan there we have the red
Channel a little higher here which means
that we have a red shirt and so on what
I like to do is use the parade which is
basically the same thing they're just
split out side by side and this makes it
easy to tell not only how bright things
are but roughly what color things are
and then if we want to do something like
change the white balance we can use
these signals to help balance it out so
I could take this offset and push this
around until this little Cloud on each
of these signals is at the same height
which means that it's going to be the
same brightness for each Channel which
means that it's going to be neutral so
it doesn't have a color cast it's going
to be white or gray right so if I can
push this offset around like this and
make those equal now we have a neutral
signal on this back wall and so you can
pick something that's white or neutral
and kind of use that to inform your
color balance that's where this is
really helpful for our Scopes I'll
switch from parade to Vector scope a
vector scope is a circular scope and it
plots all the pixels of the image at a
place within this circle the farther
away you get from from the middle of the
circle the more saturated it is and the
direction that those points move
determines its color and so if I were to
push this really orangish red we can see
the signal kind of go up towards
orangish red I were to bring this down
to cyan we see everything looks cyan and
so on it's pretty much like the color
wheel it's laid out just like the color
wheel but it graphs all of the pixels
that are in the
image if you're not familiar with Scopes
I definitely recommend the time and
pixels training with Daria here on
YouTube you can just Google how to use
vide Scopes time and pixels Daria is an
excellent teacher if you don't know who
Daria is she's one of my favorite people
and she has a really good explanation of
how to read Scopes and how those all
work so if you want to learn more about
that I'm going to let her explain that
but in resolve or Scopes kind of live
down here most of the time and you can
switch to whatever you want I usually
have this on Parade just so I can tell
how bright things are and what their
color cast is one last thing I want to
mention before we get out of the color
page are Behind These primary color
wheels there are a few different panels
up here in the upper right there's these
little three icons the color wheels
color bars and log Wheels if you switch
to color bars this is just a different
interface for doing the exact same thing
as the color wheels so this is great if
you want to just take away some green or
you know push a little bit more green
into the shot you can do that by just
moving These Bars up and down and it
might be a little bit more exact right
so if you have a little bit of a green
tinge you can just like Mouse over this
in the gain and kind of roll down on
your scroll wheel a little bit and take
away some of the green so if you prefer
something like this that's a great way
to do it but something else is the log
Wheels now this is something that's
really confusing for people this panel
is called the log Wheels but it doesn't
really have anything to do with log
footage so you don't need to use it on
log footage it's not for log footage it
has nothing to do with log footage at
all it's called log Wheels all right
just just go ahead just accept it what
this is is a similar tool let's just go
to a different shot we'll just we'll
just go to this shot right here this is
a similar tool to our color wheels in
that it splits up the image into the
darkest Parts the midtones and the
brightest parts and then kind of the
overall kind of does the same same thing
it just calls it Shadow midtone and
highlights and offsets the same and the
ways that you adjust things are similar
but instead of adjusting the entire
image and just being stronger in the
brighter Parts this highlights wheel if
I push this really pink you'll notice
almost nothing happens why is that the
reason for that is because these
highlights only adjust the image within
the highlights range so if I were to
adjust this highlights range right here
and I was to bring this down we'll see
that we can push more and more pink into
the image until I get all the way to
zero and then it's just doing everything
right and so it's kind of a threshold of
where I want to adjust this image can
double click to reset things and then
same thing for Shadows right if I make
really blue Shadows that's going to make
the darkest parts of this image really
blue but it's going to kind of cut it
off at 33% and so if I were to take this
down it's going to make less of the
image blue it's only going to make the
really dark Parts if I push this way up
it's going to make everything blue and
so it's sort of like it's split up like
the color wheels except for you have a
little bit more control over exactly
what parts of the image you want to
adjust now why would you need that most
of the time honestly you probably won't
need it what I use this for is if I want
to tint something like this window I
might be able to push like if I want to
make that window kind of yellow I can
kind of push this highlights yellow and
then take that range down until it
starts to adjust the highlights in the
window and then I could do something
like limit this with a window I'm I'm
window the window and that's a way that
you can kind of make sort of like
secondary adjustments using the color
wheels something I find myself doing a
lot is if I want cooler Shadows I like
to kind of build this into my look
sometimes is just push these Shadows
really cyan like this but then take this
lower range down and just barely start
to push that in just so it's starting to
make the really really dark midtones
tinge a little bit cyan so here's
without it and here's with it it's
almost you almost don't even notice it
it's just pushing that a little bit more
cyan makes the colors look a little bit
more richer and that's just a really
quick way to do that there's a bunch of
different ways to do that you could do
this in your curves a lot of people will
do that you could unlink the different
channels and you could push up blue in
the darker parts you know and take away
red from the darker parts like this and
that's going to give you a similar thing
you know we're kind of pushing that
bluish cyan into the darker parts of the
image but I mean that's a lot of work
when you could just grab the Shadow and
push that cyan and get a really similar
result and then just kind of dial it in
with the range so there's all these
different kinds of tools and different
ways that you use them and so if you
need to do something like that that
works now we're not going to spend a lot
of time on this but behind the primaries
are the HDR Wheels this is essentially
the same thing as the log Wheels except
for it's just gone insane so instead of
three different ranges you have six
different ranges and you can kind of
preview the ranges by holding down your
mouse on this little mask button here
and you can see this is is where this
wheel is going to affect where this
wheel is going to affect and so on and
so you can get really detailed and
adjust things here in the HDR panel and
they call this High dynamic range
because you generally only need this if
you have an image that's just really
really contrasty like you know you have
a really bright window and you want to
just affect the window and nothing else
you can kind of isolate that with this
range it makes a little bit easier
honestly I almost never use the HDR your
palette I know some people do there's a
lot of really good controls in here
especially if you're new to color I
would really recommend just stay with
the primary color wheels like here
because you can solve 90% of your
problems just with this palette alone
and when you combine the curves I mean
you can just do anything so there are so
many more things to get into here but
this video is going long enough man if
you're interested in going a little bit
deeper in color grading make sure to
check out our DCI resolve resources PDF
this is a collection of the top things
that I would recommend that you check
out if you want to learn more color it's
available right now and it's totally
free it's my gift to you let's keep
going now let's jump into the fair Light
page the fair Light page is the sixth
page over and this is where you go to
get super detailed with your audio much
like the fusion page and the color page
this is kind of like a dedicated app
this is a specialized page that shares
the same timeline as your edit page age
but is focused on its specialized task
which in the case of fair light is audio
now I have a demo timeline here and this
is if we were to open up our media pool
on the left here it's under bin six fair
Light page if you're following along
with the downloadable files again
there's a link in the description below
if you want to follow along download
this for free and I'm in fairlight page
finished right now just so that we can
see all of our fancy things so let's
take a look at the interface of fair
light of course we've kind of already
jumped into the media pool in the upper
left we have our media pool here the
only little difference is that we have a
source viewer here but it's just focused
on audio so it's easy for us to scrub
through our different audio sources here
see the waveforms and that kind of thing
because this is all audio focused right
next to the media pool we have our
effects and this is just filtered to
show you only audio effects and audio
Transitions and so this works as
expected you take an effect and you can
drag it onto any clip here in the
timeline just like you would in the edit
page this should make a ton of sense you
can also drag this onto a track which is
a little different than the edit page
you can put an effect on any track just
by dragging it onto it so if I wanted to
make this orange track all echoey I can
do that and that's kind of how the
effects work now when you drag an effect
onto something and you let go it will
bring up the panel for that effect and
this is a little different than the
other pages that usually have things to
do in the inspector but if you open up
the inspector and go to effects you'll
also have all the adjustments for the
effects here in the inspector but if you
click this little button here that'll
bring up the popup and that usually has
just a little bit nicer interface
although it's the same controls you can
usually have some visualization and that
kind of thing as well as some presets up
here in the left so I'll close that
effects panel close the inspector just
to give us some room up above we have
our meters and as I play this back we
can see our different channels and how
loud they are in all of the meters we
have controls for loudness right here
which is great if you're doing broadcast
stuff that needs to be a certain
loudness or if you're concerned with
hitting a certain loudness for YouTube
or online this is where you would do
that and then over here on the right we
have our viewer then down below we have
our playback control
and our tools and then our timeline and
this is very similar to the other pages
and the timeline acts pretty much like
the edit timeline you can zoom in by
holding alt and rolling in the scroll
wheel if you hold shift and scroll up
and down you can zoom vertically if you
hold control and zoom with your scroll
wheel you can scroll horizontally you
can zoom really really far and navigate
your timeline like this and so you can
kind of see the difference already to
where you can get really detailed with
your audio here in Fair light in fact
you can even zoom in check this out you
can zoom into to the sample level here
in fairlite where you just can't get
that detailed in the edit page there are
quite a few similarities like you can
grab these little white handles which
you can also do in the edit page to fade
Clips you can grab them and move them
around you can trim them a lot of that
stuff works in a very similar way over
here towards the right we have our mixer
I can just grab this and drag it to the
left and we can see all of our track
strips here now this is where a lot of
magic happens in Fair light you can
obviously set the levels for each of the
tracks like you would expect on a track
mixer you can set your pan like left and
right you can even do surround sound
paning but this is also where we have a
built-in EQ for each track you just
double click on this and that opens up
The Equalizer and we have some Dynamics
plugins and what this does is lets you
add compressor limiter gate that kind of
stuff to your track we'll get into this
in a little bit you can also add or
remove effects to each track here you
can quickly set your inputs for the
various tracks here if you want to
record into the timeline then of course
we have our record arm which you click
this if you want to set this track to
record when you're in recording mode you
have your solo which mutes everything
except for this track and then mute
which mutes the track track and so you
have a lot of control over your tracks
here in the mixer and also kind of on
the right side of the mixer we have the
buses which is kind of like the
different mixes that you can make from
your tracks it's sort of a different way
to group your tracks if you're not
familiar with a bus and these panels we
can hide and change around using the
buttons up top we can also open the
inspector which is going to be very
similar to what you're used to from the
edit page in fact has pretty much the
same controls also in the upper left we
have our Sound Library which this is
really cool this is a panel where you
can tell resolve where your sounds live
on your system if you go to these three
dots and say add Library you can select
a folder on your computer so like here's
an explosion pack let's say and once you
pick that folder you can just say select
folder and it will scan all of the Clips
in that folder and it will index them so
you can hit okay and now you can search
and they'll really quickly come up in
this list and you can preview these by
just double
clicking really cool so that's a quick
way to be able to pick the exact right
sound effect to put into your edit so
that's really some of the lay of the
land as far as the interface goes I'm
going to open up the media pool and go
to fairlight page and double click on
Fair Light page start and we'll just
make this a little bigger and here we
have a scene that is probably pretty
typical of you know where you would be
if you haven't done any kind of sound
editing or sound design really we just
have our basic dialogue and our
video where is he I had him and then you
pushed me then it's totally silent so
what we're going to do is we're going to
use Fair light to rebuild everything
that we should be Hearing in this scene
and it's going to be exciting so the
first thing I'll do is go over to my
media pool and here under media let's
find Fair light media and we have a
whole bunch of sounds and things here
that we can use and you're free to use
any of this for anything you want it's
our little gift to you if you get the uh
files here and so what I like to do is
go through and just think about just one
by one what kind of sounds should we be
hearing that we're not hearing just cuz
we only really have their voices
so one big one would be closing the door
and so we have some Sounds here GC house
door open we have doorknob sound there
we go house door close let's just drag
this to its own track that's going to
make a new track right here and we're
just going to line this up we can just
zoom this in a little bit and let's play
this back with spacebar look at that
that almost
works that works just out as it is
yeah that was lucky that works anytime
that we drop some audio on a track it's
a good idea to start naming that track
just call this uh door
sounds it's okay to be really specific
you can make lots of different tracks if
you want to so we'll call this door
sounds because we'll probably have some
other sounds
too like the door knob so we have some
door knob sounds I can double click this
and preview it yeah that's nice okay
let's try that
we can just trim this a little
bit let's just drag this to its own
track and we'll call this uh door sounds
too it's okay to have multiple tracks on
things let's just do something like
that yeah that works
well we have her slipping which we might
be able to use this
friction yeah that works
again I'm just going to drag this to a
new
track and you can put things on the same
track and it's totally okay to do that
it's just going to be a little bit
easier later when we're mixing things to
have stuff kind of on their own tracks
we'll call this one door sounds 2 this
one's going to be feet let's say for
now so we'll just have this kind of
slip great that should work she falls
down and we don't really hear anything
fall down but it does get his attention
right so right here we need to have some
kind of falling down sound so we have a
few different options here
destruction
glass okay
drops small box drop
concrete yeah maybe something like that
I can make an in and an out here just
like I would on the edit page drag this
down here and so let's just put this
in
okay we'll just combine this with a
couple other things here
that works just kind of Stack these for
now body
drops that's nice let's hit I for in O
for out drag this down we can kind of
mix these
together
yeah let's just have this come in right
after she slips
yeah very good and so we'll call this a
drops
One
Drops two and drops
three let's select all these and we can
right click go to change track color
we'll just make those teal for no reason
other than Teal's nice and really you
get the idea you kind of go through and
you add Clips throughout your scene and
you can really kind of build things
things out and fair light makes it easy
to do that I'll just switch back to our
finished page here and we have a lot of
sounds plugged in here just close our
media pool so we can see everything we
have our dialogue here we have some vo
from a mom character which is her kind
of yelling at the kids from the other
room hello you guys left your bikes on
the steps again we have some of the
falling down
sounds right and just a lot more things
layered in
here
H as well as this toilet flushing which
was a big part of the story because they
accidentally flushed their little alien
friend down the toilet when she fell
down and we're mixing a couple of
different toilet flushing sounds here to
kind of make that work and then we have
some music which I'll just solo here
we have some ambient sounds after the
toilet's flushing we have some kind of
natural sounds of grabbing the book
paper rustling the lid
opening and all of that is put in
afterwards and so it's really nice this
is just such a good environment to be
able to put in all of the clips and
everything that you need but you could
do most of this in the edit page and
where the fair Light page gets really
good is making the little minute tweaks
to things so this third track this is
the mom voice
over and I'm just going to add a new
track here and just put this down a
track by holding alt and hitting down
and let's solo this and listen to what
it sounds like hello you guys left your
bikes on the steps again so this is Mom
yelling hello you guys left your bikes
on the steps again but she's supposed to
be in the other room right she's
supposed to be like somewhere else in
the house hello you guys left your bikes
on the steps again and it sounds like
she's right there and so there's a
couple things that we can do here one is
we can add an effect for Reverb so if we
hit this plus button we can look at all
kinds of different effects go down to
reverb and click
Reverb and there are all kinds of little
controls and if you don't know lots
about Reverb that's okay go up here to
default and we'll just say maybe Studio
2 and see how this sounds hello you guys
left your bikes on the steps again okay
so but that's great cuz that sounds like
it's kind of farther away down in the
other room hello you guys left your
bikes on the steps again and so we're
part of the way there the other thing
that happens when your voice is kind of
in another room is you don't hear the
high parts of the voice you mostly hear
the low Parts the kind of booming parts
so we can fix that with an EQ I can
double click on this EQ here and if
you're unfamiliar with an EQ that's
basically just turning up the volume of
different frequencies in a sound and so
the higher frequencies are on the right
the lower frequencies are on the left
and this is like a graph kind of like
the curves graphs we talked about in the
color page but I can take this number
five and just kind of push this to the
left and we're just going to turn down
the volumes of the higher pitches in
mom's
voice hello you guys left your bikes on
the steps again see now that sounds like
she's farther away in the house check
this out so this is without The
Equalizer hello you guys left your bikes
on the step
again and this is with it hello you guys
left your bikes on the steps again yeah
so it sounds like she's in the other
room and you can easily add this kind of
stuff with the mixer here in fairlight
the other thing you can do is add some
Dynamics now the Dynamics if you double
click on this this is just a collection
of different filters that you can put on
your audio to help the quieter things
get louder and the louder things get
quieter and things kind of like that and
so if somebody is talking and some
things they say are loud and some things
they say are quiet you can kind of fix
that here with just one filter without
having to go in and draw little key
frames one thing you can do is just
again go here to the preset and we'll
just go to dialog compression and that's
just going to make sure that the really
loud Parts don't get too loud and it
kind of just Smooths out the uh the
volume a little bit hello you guys left
your bikes on the steps again and so
that can help with dialogue to make it
kind of sit in the space the Dynamics
the EQ as well as adding effects like
Reverb and now we have this hello you
guys left your bikes on the steps again
and it works really really well and all
of these tracks work pretty much the
same and you can add effects or change
Dynamics or EQ on all of these tracks to
make everything fit exactly how it's
supposed to and yeah great thing to do
in Fair light other thing that's really
nice is you can use buses now a bus is a
way to take multiple tracks and kind of
Route them through one track so let's
see I'll just go to my fair Light page
start just to show you this a little
better so we have these two dialogue
tracks here Isaac Hol and gwy
home where is he I had him and then you
pushed me
and if we wanted to add a effect to
these we could only add an effect to one
track at a time and we would have to
copy and paste them back and forth and
it would just be miserable and so one
thing we can do is Route these both
through a bus so if we go up to Fair
light and go to bus format we can add a
bus let's just say add bus and we're
going to make a stereo bus and we're
going to call this Dia for dialogue okay
and we'll hit okay now in our mixer if
we take this little Edge and we pull
this to the left we have our bus two
which is our dialogue bus we also have
our track one and track two which are
dialogue tracks and right now those are
both routed to bus one here on bus
outputs and so we can see if we play
this
back that we
have audio coming in on bus one but we
could switch this to bus two dialogue
like this and now as we play this
back we have our dialogue coming in here
on the right and all of our other sound
effects we've added in bus one but we
don't hear our dialogue what's the deal
with
that we don't hear them talking or
anything like that that's because bus
one is like our Master mix that's what
we're going to hear bus two we haven't
really told to do anything they're kind
of just playing into bus two and bus two
is almost like a hidden mix right now if
we hit this Plus for our dialogue bus we
can route that to bus one and so what
we're doing is we're routing both of
these tracks where we can adjust a bunch
of stuff and then we're taking this one
track and putting it into bus one so
now and now we hear them talking where
is he I had him and then you P but that
dialogue is going through this bus first
so that means that we could do something
like EQ both of these at the same time
with the same EQ and I'll just put that
Mom EQ on it the mom EQ where is he I
had him and then you pushed me right and
so we
can where is he I had him and then
adjust those both together or what's
more common is just double clicking on
this Dynamics and adding some dialogue
impression
there pushed me where is he I had him
and then you pushed me and we're
treating some of our dialogue that way
so now we kind of have a master track
for our dialogue that's bus two and you
can do this for a bunch of different
buses you could have a bus for all of
your door sounds a bus for all of your
sound effects a bus for your music and
all that stuff and you can make as many
tracks as you want I could have 30
tracks here and I could route them to
certain buses to kind of control them in
groups this is also great if you want to
export you know everything except for
the dialogue if you want to if you're
doing like a multilanguage thing or
everything except for the music if you
want to be able to edit this better
later it kind of depends on what you're
doing one other thing I want to show you
that we can do in Fair light that's just
a really nice Advantage is it's really
easy to come in and adjust your track
all you do is hold alt and you can add
little key frames here to the
volume and you can really get detailed
with how loud this stuff is and so if
you do have a part that's really loud or
really quiet you can kind of go in here
and boost it yourself which always makes
things a little bit better and come
through a little bit nicer even if
you're using a compressor or using the
Dynamics here so again if we wanted to
get really crazy with this just zoom in
here's the volume line you can push this
up or down to make this louder or
quieter and you can hold Alt or option
on a Mac and adjust this line to adjust
the volume over time now notice that we
don't have to do this to fade things out
we can just use the fade transitions
here on the edges of our Clips that's a
much quicker easier way to do that same
thing here these are crossfaded just
from the edit page and everything that
we do here if I were to fade this out
over like a big fade if I were to switch
over to the edit page look at this we
still have that big fade here we still
have some of the automation although
that's a little bit more annoying to
play with in the edit page we still have
all the track colors and all of the
clips and everything and again just like
the other Pages we don't have to render
things out or anything like that we can
just play this back and it will play
back exactly like we have in Fair light
it's just easier to get to all of the
tools to adjust this in Fair light but
it's going to sound the same in Fair
light and the edit page because it's all
happening at the same time on the same
timeline now there is a lot more to get
into with Fair light way more than I
have time to get into right now and this
video is already super long I'm also not
the world's biggest audio guy as well I
like it I appreciate it but I'm really
more about color INF fusion and doing
edits and that kind of thing we do
however have some really great audio
resources in our D Vinci resolve
resources PDF including a topnotch
course from our friend Jason yalovsky
click here to get that PDF for free if
you get it right now there's also a link
in the description but definitely
download this project file open up the
fair Light page start with the fair
Light page start and use these sound
effects and any sound effects that you
might have to make this scene a little
better you're free to use this to
practice so helpful when you're learning
to do sound design to have some nice
stuff like this that's our gift to you
all right let's finish up this course
and head over to the deliver page all
right the last page of resolve is the
deliver page this is where you're going
to actually set your settings and your
outputs and everything to render your
movie something to mention is in the
edit page if you go up to file and go to
Quick
export you can actually render quite a
few different formats that you might
want to render for your movie including
presets for YouTube Vimeo Tik Tok that
kind of thing but they don't really give
you control over the settings these are
just kind of a quick way to export
something with a
preset over here in the deliver page
this is where you can get super detailed
with if every single little thing about
the video format you're creating and
it's a pretty simple layout here in the
left hand side this is where most of the
actions going to happen these are the
render settings so these are all the
little detailed properties and
everything for the files you'll be
making up here is the viewer we also
have Clips here kind of like in the
color page and then we have our timeline
now the only difference with this
timeline is you can't do anything you
can't edit things or trim things or
anything like that the only thing you
can do is set an in and an out and so
you can decide to render just part of
your video or the whole thing by
clicking this render inout or entire
timeline like that and there's not a
whole lot else that uh you need to pay
attention to here as far as the
timelines go on the right we have our
render CU and this is just going to be a
list of jobs that you make and you can
put multiple different timelines or even
different projects and everything in
this render queue and you can have these
all render at the same time time while
you go to lunch or whatever but really I
mean the majority of the action in this
page is going to happen here in the
render settings so let's take a look at
that across the top here we have a bunch
of different presets and so these are
great starting points if you're not
really sure exactly how to set your
settings let's just start with a YouTube
preset just click on YouTube and what
that will do is change all of my
settings down here and it will give me
some limited options to be able to
change things so some of the options of
course it's going to ask for a file name
it's going to ask where to render it you
can hit browse and pick a folder on your
computer you can pick your resolution
your frame rate your video format your
codec and some other advanced settings
here but any time that you click one of
these presets it really just sets your
settings and what I like to do is just
click a preset and then go back over
here to custom export that's going to
keep all of the settings that it had but
it's going to open up a bunch more more
options for me so I can go through and
really tweak things and get just totally
crazy with all of these settings again
if you don't know all of these settings
it's not that big a deal you can
probably just click the YouTube preset
or even the h264 or h.265 Master presets
and those would be great for YouTube If
you have the paid version of resolve you
can render h265 Quicktime and O baby
that looks a lot better than h264 I
believe this also works on Mac with the
free version but the PC free version
doesn't have h265 rendering which is too
bad but that's essentially what I would
do for YouTube and if you want to get a
really good export what I would do is
just click on YouTube 1080 and then
click back to custom export and I would
change just a couple things here again
if you're on the paid version of resolve
I would click h265 here encoder I would
pick Nvidia if you have an Nvidia card
because it'll just go faster resolution
I'd like to upres this actually to alter
HD even if it's a 1080p timeline because
that's going to make YouTube actually
use a better compression on this just
because it's higher resolution and it's
going to end up looking better even
though Uprising this to Ultra HD won't
make it look better just by doing that
it's just going to kind of trick YouTube
into compressing this better the only
other thing I'd really change is this
quality I would restrict this to 2,000
times your frame rate so this is about
24 frames so we could do
48,000 kilobits per second and I found
that this is the best kind of bang for
your buck as far as how big the file
should be and how good it looks if you
do more than this you won't really
notice a difference but you'll make the
file size a lot bigger and if you do
less than this you might start to notice
a little bit of a difference in the
quality that this is actually rendering
everything else uh you could probably
leave just about as is and go over to
audio I would make sure that the data
rate is 320 kilobits per second here and
then if you switch over to file you can
change the naming conventions and stuff
if you're rendering a bunch of things
you can have these use the timeline name
which can sometimes be really helpful if
you have multiple different timelines
and you have the timelines named like
you want your videos to be named you can
just switch that to timeline and then
you can just add a bunch of these to the
render queue without having to type the
name each time but once you're ready to
add it you can go down to add to render
queue like this and just click on that
and it's going to ask me if I want to
add higher resolution renders it's
basically saying hey you're Uprising
this and that not really going to help a
whole lot you sure you want to do that
and I said yes add and now it's added a
job here in the render queue this isn't
rendering yet it isn't exporting or
doing anything yet it's just waiting and
once it's time for me to render when I'm
ready to go to lunch or stop using
resolve for a few minutes I can click
render all and that will start rendering
the cool thing about this is I can cue
multiple different versions of this same
timeline or even multiple timelines and
so let's say I want a h265 master can
just click on that and that's just going
to be a little bit bigger file little
bit higher quality add that to render
queue and I'll go over to file and here
maybe I'll make it a custom name we'll
call this HQ h265
add that maybe we want a really high
quality render of this that we could use
for years to come and re-edit and do all
kinds of stuff you can just switch to
custom export go to format QuickTime
codec let's just do dnxhr this is a
really high quality format and then you
can pick your quality from this list
basically the further you go up this
list the bigger the file but the better
quality render it makes you could
probably do like hqx 10 bit if you
wanted to or 12 bit and and then they
just get totally crazy after that but if
you want the ultimate archive and you
don't worry about taking up a bunch of
space on your computer you could do
dnxhr 444 12bit and this we don't need
to upres because we're not putting it on
YouTube for audio instead of AAC I'll do
linear PCM bit depth 32 and that's going
to give us the highest quality video and
audio that we could render out of
resolve basically and so we'll call this
archive and hit add to render q and so
now we have three different kinds of
files that we're putting out this let's
say uh maybe we're doing an interview or
something and we want to export this as
a podcast we could also go over to our
presets and click Audio Only and so it's
automatically just set these settings
it's unticked export video and for audio
we're going to pick format wave linear
PCM bit depth 24 you could also just
directly make this a MP3 that looks good
and I'll hit add to render Q so now we
have all these different kinds of
versions that we could render out let me
show you one other cool thing too let's
say we want to export the audio in
separate tracks like if we open up our
fairlight page finished timeline we have
all these different tracks here let's
say we want to export these all synced
but as different tracks so that we could
go and remix this later if we want to
here in our audio options we could say
wave linear PCM but output track one we
could change this to all timeline tracks
and what that's going to do is make a
separate file for each track in our
timeline so we can add that to render q
and that's going to be all of our audio
in separate tracks and so we can really
save this out in so many different
formats and really keep this kind of
future proof when we're ready to render
all this I can select all of this stuff
just shift select it when these are all
selected or when none of them are
selected you can hit render all and what
that will do is render all of your
footage now I made a mistake the output
of these shouldn't be 1920 x 1080 it
should be 1920 by 800 because we have
this widescreen format so if I add a job
to this and I want to adjust it I can
click this pencil and it'll ask me if I
want to save the render job I'll say
don't save that'll get rid of that and
it will load my settings here in the
render settings again and so I think
instead of 3840 by 2160 let's still
upres it but we're going to do 3840
x600 great add to render CU add and
we'll replace and we can go through and
adjust our jobs and everything I'm just
going to get rid of a couple of these in
fact I'll even make a archive file let's
just do quick time dnxhr 12bit 1920 by
800 looks good and for the audio let's
do linear PCM and output track let's do
all timeline tracks you can also click
on timeline track and pick a specific
track and then hit this button and do
like multiple different tracks like that
so I could do you know track one track
two that kind of thing you can also pick
different buses if you have several
different buses for your tracks so for
instance if we go to fusion page start
where we had a couple of buses set up
this will show me my bus one stereo as
well as my dialogue bus and so I could
do bus one and then dialogue separate
and then we can add to render queue like
this and we could render these out and
it'll create the files that we asked it
to I can right click on any of these and
say open file location that'll bring
that up on my system and I can double
click on this and actually look at my
finished product is that awesome W so
great so hopefully you've learned a ton
in this course about making your own
videos and resolve I hope this has been
really helpful for you so I know we went
over a lot in this course and if you
want a really nice little index a nice
Roundup of all the best places to learn
all of these things and dive deeper make
sure to check out our D Vinci resolve
resources PDF it's available right there
you can get it for free as an instant
download you'll also be signed up for
our newsletter to hear from yours truly
if you're interested in Fusion if you
don't know me my name is Casey and I
teach fusion and I'm so glad that I
can't believe you sat through this
entire video that's amazing if you made
it all the way to here would you leave a
comment below and let me know because
you get you get a metal of some kind of
honorable mention
a metal of honorable mention for being
so awesome and hey like I said at the
beginning of the video once you're ready
to learn Fusion I want to help you with
that so make sure to keep me in mind
when you're ready to dive into that but
until then please use everything that
you've learned to make awesome videos
Express Yourself get out of your comfort
zone and create things that didn't exist
before because that's what's magical so
I'm going to put the link to our
resources PDF right here and you can
download that totally for free and again
yeah if you want to if you want to get
into Fusion well here's here's a great
here's a great video for that all right
hey thanks for stopping by San Diego